<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://syriaca.org/documentation/syriaca-tei-main.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Sayings of the Desert Fathers, an imagined network</title>
                <editor ref="https://github.com/alexvawter">Alexandria Vawter</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>ISAW, Fall 2017</p>
                <p>Introduction to Digital Humanities</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Apophthegmata Patrum, The Alphabetical Collection</p>
                <p>translated by Benedicta Ward</p>
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
     
<div type="section" n="Anthony">
                <p n="1"> 1. When the holy Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> lived in the desert he was beset by accidie, and attacked by many sinful thoughts. He said to God, <q who="m1">'Lord,  I want to be saved but these thoughts do not leave me alone; what shall I do in my affliction? How can I be saved?'</q> A short while afterwards, when he got up to go out, <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> saw a man like himself sitting at his work, getting up from his work to pray, then sitting down and plaiting a rope, then getting up again to pray. It was an angel of the Lord sent to correct and reassure him. He heard the angel saying to him, 'Do this and you will be saved.' At these words, <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> was filled with joy and courage. He did this, and he was saved.</p>
                <p n="2"> 2. When the same Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> thought about the depth of the judgements of God, he asked,<q who="m1">'Lord, how is it that some die when they are young, while others drag on to extreme old age? Why are there those who are poor and those who are rich? Why do wicked men prosper and why are the just in need?'</q> He heard a voice answering him, '<persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>, keep your attention on yourself; these things are according to the judgement of God, and it is not to your advantage to know anything about them.'</p> 
                <p n="3"> 3. Someone asked Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> , 'What must one do in order to please God?' The old man replied, <q who="m1">'Pay attention to what I tell you: whoever you may be, always have God before your eyes; whatever you do, do it according to the testimony of the holy Scriptures; in whatever place you live, do not easily leave it. Keep these three precepts and you will be saved.'</q></p>
                <p n="4"> 4. Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, <q type="conversation" who="m1">'This is the great work of a man: always to take the blame for his own sins before God and to expect temptation to his last breath.'
                        <listPerson>
                            <person><persName ref="m1"></persName></person>
                            <listRelation><relation type="said-to" name="monk" active="m1" passive="m23"/></listRelation>
                        </listPerson></q> 
                        </p>
                <p n="5">5. He also said, 'Whoever has not experienced temptation cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.' He even added, 'Without temp- tations no-one can be saved.'</p>
                <p n="6"> 6. Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> asked Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>, 'What ought I to do?' and the old man said to him, 'Do not trust in your own righteousness, do not worry about the past, but control your tongue and your stomach.'</p> 
                <p n="7"> 7. Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'I saw the snares that the enemy spreads out over the world and I said groaning, "What can get through from such snares?" Then I heard a voice saying to me, "Humility." ' </p>
                <p n="8">8. He also said, 'Some have afflicted their bodies by asceticism,
            but they lack discernment, and so they are far from God.'</p>
                <p n="9">9. He also said, 'Our life and our death is with our neighbour. If we gain our brother, we have gained God, but if we scandalise our brother, we have sinned against Christ.'</p>
                <p n="10">10 . He said also, 'Just as fish die if they stay too long out of water, so the monks who loiter outside their cells or pass their time with men of the world lose the intensity of inner peace. So like a fish going towards the sea, we must hurry to reach our cell, for fear that if we delay outside we will lose our interior watchfulness.'</p>
               <p n="11">11. He said also, 'He who wishes to live in solitude in the desert is delivered from three conflicts: hearing, speech, and sight; there is only one conflict for him and that is with fornication.'</p>
                <p n="12">12.<persName ref="g1">Some brothers</persName> came to find Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> to tell him about the visions they were having, and to find out from him if they were true or if they came from the demons. They had a donkey which died on the way. When they reached the place where the old man was, he said to them before they could ask him anything, 'How was it that the little donkey died on the way here?' They said, 'How do you know about that, Father?' And he told them, 'The demons shewed me what happened.' So they said, 'That was what we came to question you about, for fear we were being deceived, for we have visions which often turn out to be true.' Thus the old man convinced them, by the example of the donkey, that their visions came from the demons.
                     </p>
              <p n="13">13. A <persName ref="a1">hunter</persName> in the desert saw Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> enjoying himself with the brethren and he was shocked. Wanting to show him that it was necessary sometimes to meet the needs of the brethren, the old man said to him,<q who="m1">'Put an arrow in your bow and shoot it.'</q> So he did. The old man then said, 'Shoot another,' and he did so. Then the old man said,<q who="m1">'Shoot yet again,'</q> and the hunter replied <q who="a1">'If I bend my bow so much I will break it.'</q> Then the old man said to him, <q who="m1">'It is the same with the work of God. If we stretch the brethren beyond measure they will soon break. Sometimes it is necessary to come down to meet their needs.'</q> When he heard these words the hunter was pierced by compunction and, greatly edified by the old man, he went away. As for the brethren, they went home strengthened.</p>
              <p n="14"> 14. Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> heard of a very young monk who had performed a miracle on the road. Seeing the old men walking with difficulty along the road, he ordered the wild asses to come and carry them until they reached Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName>. Those whom they had carried told Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> about it. He said to them, 'This monk seems to me to be a ship loaded with goods but I do not know if he will reach harbour.' After a while, <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> suddenly began to weep, to tear his hair and lament. His disciples said to him, 'Why are you weeping, Father?' and the old man replied, 'A great pillar of the Church has just fallen (he meant the young monk) but go to him and see what has happened.' So the disciples went and found the monk sitting on a mat and weeping for the sin he had committed. Seeing the disciples of the old man he said, 'Tell the old man to pray that God will give me just ten days and I hope I will have made satisfaction.' But in the space of five days he died.</p>
            <p n="15">   15. The brothers praised a monk before Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>. When the monk came to see him, <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> wanted to know how he would bear insults; and seeing that he could not bear them at all, he said to him, 'You are like a village magnificently decorated on the outside, but destroyed from within by robbers.'</p>
            <p n="16">  16. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>, 'Pray for me.' The old man said to him, 'I will have no mercy upon you, nor will God have any, if you yourself do not make an effort and if you do not pray to God.' '</p>
            <p n="17">  17. One day <name ref="g2">some old men</name> came to see Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>. In the midst of them was Abba <persName ref="m25">Joseph</persName>. Wanting to test them, the old man suggested a text from the Scriptures, and, beginning with the youngest, he asked them what it meant. Each gave his opinion as he was able. But to each one the old man said,<q who="m1">'You have not understood it.'</q> Last of all he said to Abba <persName ref="m25">Joseph</persName>,<q who="m1"> 'How would you explain this saying?'</q> and he replied, <q who="m25">'I do not know.'</q> Then Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said,<q who="m1">'Indeed, Abba <persName ref="m25">Joseph</persName> has found the way, for he has said: "I do not know."'</q></p>
             <p n="18"> 18.<name ref="g3">Some brothers</name> were coming from <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> to see Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName>. When they were getting into a boat to go there, they found an old man who also wanted to go there. The brothers did not know him. They sat in the boat, occupied by turns with the words of the Fathers, Scripture and their manual work. As for the old man, he remained silent. When they arrived on shore they found that the old man was going to the cell of Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> too. When they reached the place, <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said to them, 'You found this old man a good companion for the journey?' Then he said to the old man, 'You have brought many good brethren with you, father.' The old man said, 'No doubt they are good, but they do not have a door to their house and anyone who wishes can enter the stable and loose the ass.' He meant that the brethren said whatever came into their mouths.
                 <listEvent>
                     <event><desc>Some brothers from Scetis visted Anthony</desc></event> 
                     <listRelation>
                         <relation type="visited" name="vistor" active="g3" passive="m1">
                             <desc>from
                                 <location>
                                     <placeName>Scetis<addName>Wadi El Natrun</addName><geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>
                                 <geo>30.35 30.20</geo> 
                                 </location>
                             </desc></relation></listRelation></listEvent> 
                 </p>
     <p n="19">    19. The brethren came to the Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> and said to him, 'Speak a word; how are we to be saved?' The old man said to them, 'You have heard the Scriptures. That should teach you how.' But they said, 'We want to hear from you too, Father.' Then the old man said to them, 'The Gospel says, "if anyone strikes you on one cheek, turn to him the other also."' (Matt. 5.39) They said, 'We cannot do that.' The old man said, 'If you cannot offer the other cheek, at least allow one cheek to be struck.' 'We cannot do that either,' they said. So he said, 'If you are not able to do that, do not return evil for evil,' and they said, 'We cannot do that either.' Then the old man said to his disciple, 'Prepare a little brew of corn for these invalids. If you cannot do this, or that, what can I do for you? What you need is prayers.'</p>
 <p n="20">   20. A brother renounced the world and gave his goods to the poor, but he kept back a little for his personal expenses. He went to see Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName>. When he told him this, the old man said to him, 'If you want to be a monk, go into the village, buy some meat, cover your naked body with it and come here like that.' The brother did so, and the dogs and birds tore at his flesh. When he came back the old man asked him whether he had followed his advice. He showed him his wounded body, and Saint <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> said, 'Those who renounce the world but want to keep something for themselves are torn in this way by the demons who make war on them.'</p>

 <p n="21">21. It happened one day that one of the brethren in the monas- tery of Abba <persName ref="m7">Elias</persName> was tempted. Cast out of the monastery, he went over the mountain to Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>. The brother lived near him for a while and then <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> sent him back to the monastery from which he had been expelled. When the brothers saw him they cast him out yet again, and he went back to Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> saying, 'My Father, they will not receive me.' Then the old man sent them a message saying, 'A boat was shipwrecked at sea and lost its cargo; with great difficulty it reached the shore; but you want to throw into the sea that which has found a safe harbour on the shore.' When the brothers understood that it was Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> who had sent them this monk, they received him at once.</p>
        <p n="22">22. Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'I believe that the body possesses a natu- ral movement, to which it is adapted, but which it cannot follow without the consent of the soul; it only signifies in the body a movement without passion. There is another movement, which comes from the nourishment and warming of the body by eating and drinking, and this causes the heat of the blood to stir up the body to work. That is why the apostle said, "Do not get drunk with wine for that is debauchery." (Ephes. 5.18) And in the Gospel the Lord also recommends this to his disciples: "Take heed to your- selves lest your hearts be weighed down with dissipation and drunk- enness." (Luke 21:34) But there is yet another movement which afflicts those who fight, and that comes from the wiles and jealousy of the demons. You must understand what these three bodily move- ments are: one is natural, one comes from too much to eat, the third is caused by the demons.'</p>
          <p n="23">23. He also said, 'God does not allow the same warfare and temptations to this generation as he did formerly, for men are weaker now and cannot bear so much.'</p>
          <p n="24">24. It was revealed to Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> in his desert that there was one who was his equal in the city. He was a doctor by profession and whatever he had beyond his needs he gave to the poor, and every day he sang the Sanctus with the angels.</p>
         <p n="25">25. Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'A time is coming when men will go mad, and when they see someone who is not mad, they will attack him saying, "You are mad, you are not like us."'</p>
          <p n="26">26. The brethren came to Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> and laid before him a passage from Leviticus. The old man went out into the desert, secretly followed by Abba Ammonas, who knew that this was his custom. Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> went a long way off and stood there praying, crying in a loud voice, 'God, send Moses, to make me under- stand this saying.' Then there came a voice speaking with him. Abba Ammonas said that although he heard the voice speaking with him, he could not understand what it said. </p>
         <p n="27">27. Three Fathers used to go and visit blessed <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> every year and two of them used to discuss their thoughts and the salva- tion of their souls with him, but the third always remained silent and did not ask him anything. After a long time, Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said to him, 'You often come here to see me, but you never ask me any- thing,' and the other replied, 'It is enough for me to see you, Father.'</p>
          <p n="28">28. They said that a certain old man asked God to let him see the Fathers and he saw them all except Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>. So he asked his guide, 'Where is Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>?' He told him in reply that in the place where God is, there <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> would be.</p>
          <p n="29">29. A brother in a monastery was falsely accused of fornication and he arose and went to Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>. The brethren also came from the monastery to correct him and bring him back. They set about proving that he had done this thing, but he defended himself and denied that he had done anything of the kind. Now Abba Paphnutius, who is called Cephalus, happened to be there, and he told them this parable: 'I have seen a man on the bank of the river buried up to his knees in mud and some men came to give him a hand to help him out, but they pushed him further in up to his neck.' Then Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said this about Abba Paphnutius: 'Here is a real man, who can care for souls and save them.' All those present were pierced to the heart by the words of the old man and they asked forgiveness of the brother. So, admonished by the Fathers, they took the brother back to the monastery.</p>
         <p n="30">30. Some say of Saint <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> that he was 'Spirit-borne', that is, carried along by the Holy Spirit, but he would never speak of this to men. Such men see what is happening in the world, as well as knowing what is going to happen.
31. One day Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> received a letter from the Emperor Constantius, asking him to come to Constantinople and he won- dered whether he ought to go. So he said to Abba Paul, his disciple, 'Ought I to go?' He replied, 'If you go, you will be called <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName>; but if you stay here, you will be called Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName>.'</p>
         <p n="32">32. Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> said, 'I no longer fear God, but I love Him. For love casts out fear.'(John 4.18)</p>
       <p n="33">33. He also said, 'Always have the fear of God before your eyes. Remember him who gives death and life. Hate the world and all that is in it. Hate all peace that comes from the flesh. Renounce this life, so that you may be alive to God. Remember what you have prom- ised God, for it will be required of you on the day of judgement. Suffer hunger, thirst, nakedness, be watchful and sorrowful; weep, and groan in your heart; test yourselves, to see if you are worthy of God; despise the flesh, so that you may preserve your souls.'</p>
       <p n="34">34. Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> once went to visit Abba Amoun in Mount Nitria and when they met, Abba Amoun said, 'By your prayers, the number of the brethren increases, and some of them want to build more cells where they may live in peace. How far away from here do you think we should build the cells?' Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'Let us eat at the ninth hour and then let us go out for a walk in the desert and explore the country.' So they went out into the desert and they walked until sunset and then Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'Let us pray and plant the cross here, so that those who wish to do so may build here. Then when those who remain there want to visit those who have come here, they can take a little food at the ninth hour and then come. If they do this, they will be able to keep in touch with each other without distraction of mind.' The distance is twelve miles.</p>
   <p n="35">35. Abba <persName ref="m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'Whoever hammers a lump of iron, first decides what he is going to make of it, a scythe, a sword, or an axe. Even so we ought to make up our minds what kind of virtue we want to forge or we labour in vain.'</p>
  <p n="36">36. He also said, 'Obedience with abstinence gives men power over wild beasts.'</p>
 <p n="37">37. He also said, 'Nine monks fell away after many labours and were obsessed with spiritual pride, for they put their trust in their
own works and being deceived they did not give due heed to the commandment that says, "Ask your father and he will tell you." ' (Deut. 32.7)</p>
  <p n="38">38. And he said this, 'If he is able to, a monk ought to tell his elders confidently how many steps he takes and how many drops of water he drinks in his cell, in case he is in error about it.'</p>
             
            </div>
<div type="section" n="Bessarion">
    <p n="1">  1. Abba <persName ref="m26">Doulas</persName>, the disciple of Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName> said, 'One day when we were walking beside the sea I was thirsty and I said to Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName>,<q who="m26"> "Father, I am very thirsty."</q> He said a prayer and said to me,<q who="m2"> "Drink some of the sea water."</q> The water proved sweet when I drank some. I even poured some into a leather bottle for fear of being thirsty later on. Seeing this, the old man asked me why I was taking some. I said to him, <q who="m26">"Forgive me, it is for fear of being thirsty later on."</q> Then the old man said, <q who="m2">"God is here, God is everywhere."'<listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m2"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m2" passive="m26"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></q></p>
    <p n="2">   2. Another time when Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName> had occasion to do so, he said a prayer and crossed the river Chrysoroas on foot and then continued his way. Filled with wonder, I asked his pardon and said, 'How did your feet feel when you were walking on the water?' He replied, <q who="m2">'I felt the water just to my heels, but the rest was dry.'</q> </p>
    <p n="3">     3. On another day, while we were going to see an old man, the sun was setting. So Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName> said this prayer,<q who="m2">'I pray you, Lord, that the sun may stand still till we reach your servant,'</q> and that is what happened.</p>
    <p n="4">    4. On another day, when I came to his cell I found him standing at prayer with his hands raised towards heaven. For fourteen days he remained thus. Then he called me and told me to follow him. We went into the <placeName>desert</placeName>. Being thirsty, I said to him, 'Father, I am thirsty.' Then, taking my sheepskin, the old man went about a stone's throw away and when he had prayed, he brought it back, full of water. Then we walked on and came to a cave where, on entering we found a brother seated, engaged in plaiting a rope. He did not raise his eyes to us, nor greet us, since he did not want to enter into conversation with us. So the old man said to me, 'Let us go; no doubt the old man is not sure if he ought to speak with us.' We continued our journey towards <placeName>Lycopolis<geo>31.5 30.57</geo></placeName>, till we reached Abba John's cell. After greeting him, we prayed, then the old man sat down to speak of the vision which he had had. Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName> said it had been made known to him that the temples would be overthrown. That is what happened: they were overthrown. On our return, we came again to the cave where we had seen the brother. The old man said to me, 'Let us go in and see him; perhaps God has told him to speak to us.' When we had entered, we found him dead. The old man said to me, 'Come, brother, let us take the body; it is for this reason God has sent us here.' When we took the body to bury it we perceived that it was a woman. Filled with astonishment, the old man said, 'See how the women triumph over Satan, while we still behave badly in the towns.' Having given thanks to God, who protects those who love him, we went away.   <listEvent>
        <event><desc>Bessarion and a man travel into the desert and then to Lycopolis</desc></event> 
        <listRelation><relation type="traveled-to" name="traveler" active="m2" passive="p2">
            <desc>
                <placeName>Lycopolis<geo>31.5 30.57</geo></placeName>
            </desc></relation>
        </listRelation>
    </listEvent> </p>
    <p n="5">  5. One day a <persName ref="a2">man possessed with a devil</persName> came to <placeName ref="p1">Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, and they prayed over him, but the devil did not leave him, for it was obstinate. The priests said, 'What can we do against this devil? No one can drive him away, except Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName>, but if we call him, he will not come, even to the church. Therefore let us do this: since he comes to church early, before anyone else, let us make the possessed sleep here and when he comes, let us keep to our prayer, and say to him, "Abba, awaken the brother." ' This is what they did. When the old man came early, they kept to their prayer and said to him, 'Awaken the brother.' The old man said to him,<q who="m2">'Arise and go.'</q> Immediately the devil departed from him and from that hour he was healed. <listEvent><event><desc>Bessarion lived in Scetis</desc></event> 
        <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m2" passive="p1">
            <desc>in
                <placeName ref="p2">Lycopolis<geo>31.5 30.57</geo></placeName>
            </desc></relation>
        </listRelation>
        </listEvent> 
    </p>
      <p n="6">    6. Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName> said, <q who="m2">'For fourteen days and nights, I have stood upright in the midst of thorn-bushes, without sleeping.'</q></p>
      <p n="7">   7. A brother who had sinned was turned out of the church by the priest; Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName> got up and went with him, saying, <q who="m2">'I, too, am a sinner.'</q></p>
    <p n="8">   8. The same Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName> said, <q who="m2">'For fourteen years I have never lain down, but have always slept sitting or standing.'</q></p>
    <p n="9">      9. The same abba said, <q who="m2">'When you are at peace, without having to struggle, humiliate yourself for fear of being led astray by joy which is inappropriate; we magnify ourselves and we are delivered to warfare. For often, because of our weakness, God does not allow us to be tempted, for fear we should be overcome.'</q></p>
    <p n="10">  10. A <persName ref="a3">brother</persName> who shared a lodging with other brothers asked Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName>, <q who="a3">'What should I do?'</q> The old man replied, <q who="m2">'Keep silence and do not compare yourself with others.'</q><listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m2"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m2" passive="a3"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></p>
    <p n="11">   11. Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName>, at the point of death, said, <q who="m2">'The monk ought to be as the Cherubim and the Seraphim: all eye.'</q></p>
    <p n="12">   12. Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName>'s disciples related that his life had been like that of a bird of the air, or a fish, or an animal living on earth, passing all the time of his life without trouble or disquiet. The care of a dwelling did not trouble him, and the desire for a particular place never seemed to dominate his soul, no more than the abundance of delights, or the possession of houses or the reading of books. But he seemed entirely free from all the passions of the body, sustaining himself on the hope of good things to come, firm in the strength of his faith; he lived in patience, like a prisoner who is led everywhere, always suffering cold and nakedness, scorched by the sun. He always lived in the open air, afflicting himself on the edge of the desert like a vagabond. Often he found it good to be carried over the sea to distant and uninhabited regions. When he happened to come into pleasanter places where the brethren lived a life in common, he would sit outside at the gate, weeping and lamenting like one shipwrecked and flung back on to the earth. Then if <persName ref="a4">one of the brethren</persName> coming out found him there, sitting like one of the poor beggars living in the world, and filled with compassion approached him, asking, <q who="a4">'Man, why are you weeping? If you are in need of something, as far as we can we will see you receive it, only come in, share our table and rest yourself.'</q> He would reply,<q who="m2"> 'I cannot live under a roof so long as I have not found again the riches of my house,'</q> adding that he had lost great riches in various ways. <q who="m2">'I have fallen amongst pirates, I have suffered shipwreck, I have dishonoured my rank, becoming unknown, famous as I was.' </q>The brother, moved by these words, returned, bringing a morsel of bread and giving it him, saying,<q who="a4"> 'Take this, Father; all the rest, as you say, God will restore to you; home, honour, and riches of which you speak.'</q> But he, bewailing himself yet more, sighed deeply, adding, <q who="m2">'I cannot say if I shall find again those lost good things I seek, but I am still more afflicted, every day suffering the danger of death, having no respite because of my great calamities. For always I must wander, in order to finish my course.'</q><listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m2"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m2" passive="a4"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson> </p>
  </div>  
<div type="section" n="Benjamin">
    <p>1. Abba <persName ref="m3">Benjamin</persName> said, <q who="m3">'When we returned to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, once the harvest was over, in payment they brought each of us a plaster vessel containing a pint of oil from Alexandria. When the time of harvest came again, the brothers brought what was left to the church. For my own part, I had not uncorked my vessel but had taken a little by piercing it with a stiletto, imagining in my heart that I had achieved something splendid. But when the brothers brought their plaster vessels as they were while mine was pierced, I was as ashamed as though I had committed fornication.'</q></p>
   <p> 2. Abba <persName ref="m3">Benjamin</persName>, priest of the Cells, said, <q who="m3">'One day at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> we went to an old man, intending to take him a little oil but he said to us, "Look at the little vessel you brought me three years ago; it has remained there where you put it." At these words we wondered at the old man's virtue.'</q></p>
    <p>  3. The same abba said, <q who="m3">'We went to another old man who detained us for a meal and he offered us oil of horseradish. We said to him, "Father, give us rather a little good oil." At these words he crossed himself and said, 'I did not know there was any other kind.'</q></p>
    <p> 4. As he was dying, Abba <persName ref="m3">Benjamin</persName> said to <persName ref="a5">his sons</persName>, <q who="m3">'If you observe the following, you can be saved, "Be joyful at all times, pray without ceasing and give thanks for all things." '</q><listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m3"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="said-to" name="monk" active="m3" passive="a5"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></p>
    <p>5. He also said, <q who="m3">'Walk in the royal way, measuring the landmarks without meanness.'</q></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Daniel">
    <p>1.It was said concerning Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName>, that when the barbarians invaded <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> and the Fathers fled away, the old man said, <q who="m4">'If God does not care for me, why still live?'</q> Then he passed through the midst of the barbarians without being seen. He said to himself therefore, <q who="m4">'See how God has cared for me, since I am not dead. Now I will do that which is human and flee with the Fathers.'</q></p>
    <p> 2. <persName ref="a6">A brother</persName> asked Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName>,<q who="a5"> 'Give me a commandment and I will keep it.'</q> He replied, <q who="m4">'Never put your hand in the dish with a woman, and never eat with her; thus you will escape a little the demon of fornication.'</q> <listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m4"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m4" passive="a5"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></p>
        <p>3. Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName> said, <q who="m4">'At Babylon the daughter of an important person was possessed by a devil. A monk for whom her father had a great affection said to him, "No-one can heal your daughter except some anchorites whom I know; but if you ask them to do so, they will not agree because of their humility. Let us therefore do this: when they come to the market, look as though you want to buy their goods and when they come to receive the price, we will ask them to say a prayer and I believe she will be healed."</q> When they came to the market they found a disciple of the old men setting there selling their goods and they led him away with the baskets, so that he should receive the price of them. But when the monk reached the house, the woman possessed with the devil came and slapped him. But he only turned the other cheek, according to the Lord's Command. (Matt. 539) <persName ref="a7">The devil</persName>, tortured by this, cried out, <q who="a7">"What violence! The commandment of Jesus drives me out."</q> Immediately the woman was cleansed. When the old men came, they told them what had happened and they glorified God saying, "This is how the pride of the devil is brought low, through the humility of the commandment of Christ." '</p>
        <p>4. Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName> also said, <q who="m4">'The body prospers in the measure in which the soul is weakened, and the soul prospers in the measure in which the body is weakened.'</q></p>
    <p> 5. One day Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName> and Abba <persName ref="m27">Ammoes</persName> went on a journey together. Abba <persName ref="m27">Ammoes</persName> said, <q who="m27">'When shall we, too, settle down, in a cell, Father?'</q> Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName> replied, <q who="m4">'Who shall separate us henceforth from God? God is in the cell, and, on the other hand, he is outside also.'</q><listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m4"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m4" passive="m27"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></p>
       <p> 6. Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName> said that when Abba <persName ref="m28">Arsenius</persName> was at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, there was a monk there who used to steal the possessions of the old men. Abba <persName ref="m28">Arsenius</persName> took him into his cell in order to convert him and to give the old men some peace. He said to him, <q who="m28">'Everything you want I will get for you, only do not steal.'</q> So he gave him gold, coins, clothes and everything he needed. But the brother began to steal again. So the old men, seeing that he had not stopped, drove him away saying, <q who="m28">'If there is a brother who commits a sin through weakness, one must bear it, but if he steals, drive him away, for it is hurtful to his soul and troubles all those who live in the neighbourhood.'</q></p>
        <p>7. This is what Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName>, the Pharanite, said, <q who="m4">'Our Father Abba <persName ref="m28">Arsenius</persName> told us of an inhabitant of <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, of notable life and of simple faith; through his naivete he was deceived and said, "The bread which we receive is not really the body of Christ, but a symbol." Two old men having learnt that he had uttered this saying, knowing that he was outstanding in his way of life, knew that he had not spoken through malice, but through simplicity. So they came to find him and said, "Father, we have heard a proposition contrary to the faith on the part of someone who says that the bread which we receive is not really the body of Christ, but a symbol." The old man said, "It is I who have said that." Then the old men exhorted him saying, "Do not hold this position, Father, but hold one in conformity with that which the catholic Church has given us. We believe, for our part, that the bread itself is the body of Christ and that the cup itself is his blood and this in all truth and not a symbol. But as in the beginning, God formed man in his image, taking the dust of the earth, without anyone being able to say that it is not the image of God, even though it is not seen to be so; thus it is with the bread of which he said that it is his body; and so we
        believe that it is really the body of Christ." The old man said to them, "As long as I have not been persuaded by the thing itself, I shall not be fully convinced." So they said, "Let us pray God about this mystery throughout the whole of this week and we believe that God will reveal it to us." The old man received this saying with joy and he prayed in these words, "Lord, you know that it is not through malice that I do not believe and so that I may not err through ignorance, reveal this mystery to me, Lord Jesus Christ." The old men returned to their cells and they also prayed God, saying, "Lord Jesus Christ, reveal this mystery to the old man, that he may believe and not lose his reward." God heard both the prayers. At the end of the week they came to church on Sunday and sat all three on the same mat, the old man in the middle. Then their eyes were opened and when the bread was placed on the holy table, there appeared as it were a little child to these three alone. And when the priest put out his hand to break the bread, behold
        an angel descended from heaven with a sword and poured the child's blood into the chalice. When the priest cut the bread into small pieces, the angel also cut the child in pieces. When they drew near to receive the sacred elements the old man alone received amorsel of bloody flesh. Seeing this he was afraid and cried out, "Lord, I believe that this bread is your flesh and this chalice your blood." Immediately the flesh which he held in his hand became bread, according to the mystery and he took it, giving thanks to God. Then the old men said to him, "God knows human nature and that man cannot eat raw flesh and that is why he has changed his body into bread and his blood into wine, for those who receive it in faith." Then they gave thanks to God for the old man, because he had allowed him not to lose the reward of his labour. So all three returned with joy to their own cells.'</q></p>
    <p>8. The same Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName> told of another great old man who dwelt in lower Egypt, who in his simplicity, said that Melchizedek was the son of God. When blessed <persName ref="n1">Cyril<addName>Archbishop of <placeName ref="p3">Alexandria</placeName></addName></persName>, was told about this he sent someone to him. Learning that the old man was a worker of miracles and that all he asked of God was revealed to him, and that it was because of his simplicity that he had given utterance to this saying, using guile the Archbishop said to him, <q who="n1">'Abba, I think that Melchizedek is the son of God, while a contrary thought says to me, no, that he is simply a man, high-priest of God. Since I am thus plagued, I have sent someone to you that you may pray God to reveal to you what he is.'</q> Confident of his gift, the old man said without hesitation, <q who="m4">'Give me three days, I will ask God about this matter and I will tell you who he is.'</q> So he withdrew and prayed to God about this question. Coming three days later he said to the blessed Cyril that Melchizedek was a man. The archbishop said to him, <q who="n1">'How to you know, Abba?'</q> He replied, <q who="m4">'God has shewn me all the patriarchs in such a way that each one, from Adam to Melchizedek, passed before me. Therefore be sure that it is so.'</q> Then the old man withdrew, having preached to himself that Melchizedek was a man. Then the blessed Cyril rejoiced greatly.<listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m4"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m4" passive="n1"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Zeno">
    <p>1. Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName>, the disciple of blessed Silvanus said, <q who="m5">'Do not live in a famous place, do not settle close to a man with a great name, and do not lay foundations for building yourself a cell one day.'</q></p>
    <p>2. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName>, that from the outset he never wished to receive anything from anyone at all. Those who brought him something came away hurt that he had not accepted anything. Others came to him, wanting to receive some token from a great old man and he had nothing to give them so they too came away hurt. The old man said, <q who="m5">'What shall I do, since those who bring things are hurt just as much as those who wish to receive something?
        I know what seems right to me: when someone brings me something, I will accept it and I will give it to anyone who asks me for something.'</q> So he did that and was at peace and satisfied everyone.</p>
    <p>3. An <persName ref="a13">Egyptian brother</persName> came to see Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName> in <placeName ref="p2">Syria<geo>37.5 37.5</geo></placeName>, and accused himself to the old man about his temptations. Filled with admiration, <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName> said, <q who="m5">'The Egyptians hide the virtues they possess and ceaselessly accuse themselves of faults they do not have, while the Syrians and Greeks pretend to have virtues they do not have, and hide the faults of which they are guilty.'</q><listEvent><event><desc>Zeno lived in Syria</desc></event> 
        <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m5" passive="p4">
            <desc>in
                <placeName ref="p2">Syria<geo>37.5 37.5</geo></placeName>
            </desc></relation>
        </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
             <listEvent>
                 <event><desc>An brother from Egypt visted Zeno in Syria</desc></event> 
                 <listRelation><relation type="traveled-to" name="traveler" active="a13" passive="p8">
                     <desc>from
                         <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13</geo></placeName>
                         to <placeName ref="p2">Syria<geo>37.5 37.5</geo></placeName>
                     </desc></relation>
                 </listRelation>
             </listEvent>
 </p>
    <p>4. <persName ref="a8">Some brothers</persName> came to see him and asked him, <q who="a8">'What does this saying in the book of Job mean: "Heaven is not pure in his presence?" '</q> (Job 15.15) The old man replied, <q who="m5">'The brothers have passed over their sins and inquired about heavenly things. This is the interpretation of this saying: "God alone is pure," therefore he said, "Heaven is not pure." '</q><listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m5"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m5" passive="a8"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></p>
   <p> 5. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName>, that when he was living in <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, he came out of his cell by night, going in the direction of the marshes. He spent three days and three nights wandering at random. At last, tired out, his strength failing him, he fell down as though he were dying. Behold, a little child stood before him with bread and a jar of water and said to him, 'Get up, and eat.' He stood up and prayed, thinking that it was a delusion. The other said to him, 'You have done well.' And he prayed a second, and then a third time. The child said again, 'You have done well.' Then the old man stood up, took some food and ate. The child said to him, 'As far as you have walked, so far are you from your cell. So then, get up, and follow me.' Immediately he found himself in his cell. So the old man said to the child, 'Enter, and let us pray.' But when the old man went inside, the other vanished.
       <listEvent><event><desc>Zeno lived in Scetis</desc></event> 
           <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m5" passive="p1">
               <desc>in
                   <placeName ref="p2">Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>
               </desc></relation>
           </listRelation>
       </listEvent></p>
    
    <p>6. Another time, the same Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName> was walking in <placeName ref="p5">Palestine<geo>32.5  37.5</geo></placeName> and he was tired. He sat down near a cucumber plant to eat and he said to himself, <q who="m5">'Take a cucumber and eat it. Truly it is only a little thing.'</q> But he answered himself, <q who="m5">'Thieves are taken away to punishment. Examine yourself therefore, to see if you can bear punish- ment.'</q> He got up and stood in the sun for five days. When he was quite burnt he said, <q who="m5">'You cannot bear punishment,'</q> and he said to
        his thoughts, <q who="m5">'Since you cannot bear punishment, do not steal, and do not eat.'</q><listEvent>
            <event><desc>Zeno walked in Palestine</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="traveled-to" name="traveler" active="m5" passive="p5">
                <desc>walked in
                    <placeName ref="p5">Palestine<geo>32.5  37.5</geo></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent></p>
    
    <p>7. Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName> said, <q who="m5">'If a man wants God to hear his prayer quickly, then before he prays for anything else, even his own soul, when he stands and stretches out his hands towards God, he must pray with all his heart for his enemies. Through this action God will hear everything that he asks.'</q></p>
    <p>8. In a village there was said to be a man who fasted to such a degree that he was called '<persName ref="a9">the Faster</persName>'. Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName> had heard of him, and he sent for him. The other came gladly. They prayed and sat down. The old man began to work in silence. Since he could not succeed in talking to him the Faster began to get bored. So he said to the old man, <q who="a9">'Pray for me, Abba, for I want to go.'</q> The old man said to him. <q who="m5">'Why?'</q> The other replied, <q who="a9">'Because my heart is as if it were on fire and I do not know what is the matter with it. For truly, when I was in the village and I fasted until the evening, nothing like this happened to me.'</q> The old man said, <q who="m5">'In the village you fed yourself through your ears. But go away and from now on eat at the ninth hour and whatever you do, do it secretly.'</q> As soon as he had begun to act on this advice, the Faster found it difficult to wait until the ninth hour. And those who knew him said, 'The Faster is possessed by the devil.' So he went to tell all this to the old man who said to him, <q who= "m5">'This way is according to God.'</q><listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m5"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m5" passive="a9"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></p>
</div>            
<div type="section" n="Zacharias">
    <p>1. Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said to Abba <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName>, <q who="m21">'Tell me, what is the work of a monk?'</q> He said to him, <q who="m6">'How is it that you are asking me, Father?'</q> Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said, <q who="m21">'<persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName>, my child, you inspire me with confidence. It is God who urges me to ask you.'</q> Then <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName> said to him, <q who="m6">'Father, in my opinion, he is a monk who does violence to himself in everything.'</q></p>
    <p> 2. Going to draw water one day, Abba <persName ref="m30">Moses</persName> found Abba <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName> praying beside the well and the spirit of God rested above him.</p>
    <p> 3. One day Abba <persName ref="m30">Moses</persName> said to brother <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName>, <q who="m30">'Tell me what I ought to do?'</q> At these words the latter threw himself on the ground at the old man's feet and said, <q who="m6">'Are you asking me, Father?'</q> The old man said to him, <q who="m30">'Believe me, <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName>, my son, I have seen the Holy Spirit descending upon you and since then I am constrained to ask you.'</q> Then <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName> drew his hood off his head put it under his feet and trampled on it, saying, <q who="m6">'The man who does not let himself be treated thus, cannot become a monk.'</q></p>
       <p> 4. While he was sitting one day in <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, Abba <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName> had a vision. He went to tell his father, Carion, about it. The old man, who was an ascetic, did not understand this matter. He got up and beat him soundly, saying that it came from the demons. But <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName> went on thinking about it, and he went by night to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, to tell the matter to him and how his heart burned within him. Then the old man, seeing that this came from God, said to him, <q who="m23">'Go to such and such an old man and whatever he tells you to do, do it.'</q> <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName> went to the old man and even before he could ask anything, he forestalled him, telling him everything that had happened and saying that this vision came from God. <q who="m23">'But go,'</q> he said, <q who="m30">'and submit yourself to your father.'</q>
           <listEvent>
               <event><desc>Zacharias sat in Scetis</desc></event> 
           <listRelation><relation type="traveled-to" name="traveler" active="m6" passive="p1">
               <desc>walked in
                   <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>
               </desc></relation>
           </listRelation>
           </listEvent>
           <listPerson>
               <person><persName ref="m6"></persName></person>
               <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m6" passive="m23"/></listRelation>
           </listPerson>
       </p>
    
        <p>5. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said that Abba <persName ref="m30">Moses</persName> asked Abba <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName>, who was at the point of death, <q who="m30">'What do you see?'</q> He said, <q who="m6">'Is it not better to hold my peace, Father?'</q> And he said, <q who="m30">'Yes, it is better to hold your peace, my child.'</q> At the hour of his death, Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName> who was sitting there looked towards heaven and said, <q who="m13">'Rejoice, <persName ref="m6">Zacharias</persName>, my son, because the doors of the kingdom of heaven are opened to you.'</q></p>
    <listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m6"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m6" passive="m30,m23,m13"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson>
</div> 
<div type="section" n="Elias">
        <p>1. Abba <persName ref="m7">Elias</persName> said, <q who="m7">'For my part: I fear three things: the moment when my soul will leave my body, and when I shall appear before God, and when the sentence will be given against me.'</q></p>
       <p> 2. The <persName ref="a11">old men</persName> said of Abba <persName ref="m31">Agathon</persName> to Abba <persName ref="m7">Elias</persName>, in <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName>, <q who="a11">'He is a good abba.'</q> The old man answered them, <q who="m7">'In comparison with his own generation, he is good.'</q> They said to him, <q who="a11">'And what is he in comparison with the ancients?'</q> He gave them this answer, <q who="m7">'I have said to you that in comparison with his generation he is good but as to that of the ancients, in <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> I have seen a man who, like Joshua the son of Nun could make the sun stand still in the heavens.'</q> At these words they were astounded and gave glory to God.
           <listPerson>
               <person><persName ref="m7"></persName></person>
               <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m7" passive="a11"/></listRelation>
           </listPerson>
           <listEvent>
               <event><desc>Elias lived in Egypt</desc></event> 
               <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m7" passive="p8">
                   <desc>lived in
                       <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13</geo></placeName>
                   </desc></relation>
               </listRelation>
           </listEvent>
       </p>
       <p> 3. Abba <persName ref="m7">Elias</persName>, the minister, said, <q who="m7">'What can sin do where there is penitence? And of what use is love where there is pride?'</q></p>
    <p> 4. Abba <persName ref="m7">Elias</persName> said, <q who="m7">'I saw someone who was carrying a skin of wine on his arm, and, in order to make the demons blush, for it was a fantasy, I said to the brother, "Of your charity take off your cloak." He took off his cloak, and was not found to be carrying anything. I say that so that you may not believe even that which you see or hear. Even more, observe your thoughts, and beware of what you have in your heart and your spirit, knowing that the demons put ideas into you so as to corrupt your soul by making it think of that which is not right, in order to turn your spirit from the consideration of your sins and of God.'</q></p>
    <p> 5. He also said, <q who="m7">'Men turn their minds either to their sins, or to Jesus, or to men.'</q></p>
    <p>6. He also said, <q who="m7">'If the spirit does not sing with the body, labour is in vain. Whoever loves tribulation will obtain joy and peace later on.'</q></p>
    <p> 7. He also said, <q who="m7">'An old man was living in a temple and the demons came to say to him, "Leave this place which belongs to us," and the old man said, "No place belongs to you." Then they began to scatter his palm leaves about, one by one, and the old man went on gathering them together with perseverance. A little later the devil took his hand and pulled him to the door. When the old man reached the door, he seized the lintel with the other hand crying out, "Jesus, save me." Immediately the devil fled away. Then the old man began to weep. Then the Lord said to him, "Why are you weeping?" and the old man said, "Because the devils have dared to seize a man and treat him like this." The Lord said to him, "You had been careless. As soon as you turned to me again, you see I was beside you." I say this, because it is necessary to take great pains, and anyone who does not do so, cannot come to his God. For he himself was crucified for our sake.'</q></p>
       <p> 8. <persName ref="a12">A brother</persName> who followed the life of stillness in the monastery of the cave of Abba <persName ref="m32">Saba</persName> came to Abba <persName ref="m7">Elias</persName> and said to him, <q who="a12">'Abba, give me a way of life.'</q> The old man said to the brother, <q who="m7">'In the days of our predecessors they took great care about these three virtues: poverty, obedience and fasting. But among monks nowadays ava- rice, self-confidence and great greed have taken charge. Choose whichever you want most.'</q>
           <listPerson>
               <person><persName ref="m7"></persName></person>
               <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m7" passive="a12"/></listRelation>
           </listPerson>
           
    </p>
</div>            
<div type="section" n="Theodore of Pherme">
    <p> 1. Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore <addName>of <placeName ref="p9">Pherme<geo>30.776003 30.368868</geo></placeName></addName></persName> had acquired three good books. He came to Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> and said to him, <q who="m8">'I have three excellent books from which I derive profit; the brethren also make use of them and derive profit from them. Tell me what I ought to do: keep them for my use and that of the brethren, or sell them and give the money to the poor?'</q> The old man answered him in this way, <q who="m21">'Your actions are good; but it is best of all to posses nothing.'</q> Hearing that, he went and sold his books and gave the money for them to the poor.
        <listPerson>
            <person><persName ref="m8"></persName></person>
            <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m8" passive="m21"/></listRelation>
        </listPerson>
        <listEvent>
            <event><desc>Theodore lived in Pherme</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m8" passive="p9">
                <desc>lived in
                    <placeName ref="p9">Pherme<geo>30.776003 30.368868</geo><addName>Kellia</addName></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
    </p>
        <p>2. <persName ref="a14">A brother</persName> lived in the Cells and in his solitude he was troubled. He went to tell Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore of Pherme</persName> about it. The old man said to him, <q who="m8">'Go, be more humble in your aspirations, place yourself under obedience and live with others.'</q> Later, he came back to the old man and said, <q who="a14">'I do not find any peace with others.'</q> The old man said to him, <q who="m8">'If you are not at peace either alone or with others, why have you become a monk? Is it not to suffer trials? Tell me how many years you have worn the habit?'</q> He replied, <q who="a14">'For eight years.'</q> Then the old man said to him, <q who="m8">'I have worn the habit seventy years and on no day have I found peace. Do you expect to obtain peace in eight years?'</q> At these words the brother went away strengthened.</p>
    <p>   3. A brother came to Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> and spent three days begging him to say a word to him without getting any reply. So he went away grieved. Then the old man's disciple said to him, 'Abba, why did you not say a word to him? See, he has gone away grieved.' The old man said to him, <q who="m8">'I did not speak to him, for he is a trafficker who seeks to glorify himself through the words of others.'</q></p>
    <p> 4. He also said, <q who="m8">'If you are friendly with someone who happens to fall into the temptation of fornication, offer him your hand, if you can, and deliver him from it. But if he falls into heresy and you cannot persuade him to turn from it, separate yourself quickly from him, in case, if you delay, you too may be dragged down with him into the pit.</q></p>
        <p>5. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore of Pherme</persName> that the three things he held to be fundamental were: poverty, asceticism, flight from men.</p>
    <p> 6. One day Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> was entertaining himself with the brethren. While they were eating, they drank their cups with respect, but in silence, without even saying 'pardon'. So Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> said, <q who="m8">'The monks have lost their manners and do not say, "pardon."'</q></p>
    <p>7. A brother questioned him saying, 'Abba, would you approve of my not eating bread for several days?' The old man said to him, <q who="m8">'You do well, and I have done the same.'</q> The brother said, 'I mean to take my chickpeas to the bakery, and have them made into flour.' The old man replied, '<q who="m8">If you are going to the bakery, why not make the flour into bread? What need is there to go out twice?'</q></p>
    <p> 8. One of the old men came to Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> and said to him, 'Look how such and such a brother has returned to the world.' The old man said to him, <q who="m8">'Does that surprise you? No, rather be astonished when you hear that someone has been able to escape the jaws of the enemy.'</q></p>
    <p>9. A brother came to Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> and began to converse with him about things which he had never yet put into practice. So the old man said to him, <q who="m8">'You have not yet found a ship nor put your cargo aboard it and before you have sailed, you have already arrived at the city. Do the work first; then you will have the speed you are making now.'</q></p>
    <p>10. The same abba came one day to see Abba John, a eunuch from birth, and during their conversation he said to him, <q who="m8">"When I was at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, the works of the soul were our work, and we considered manual work to be subordinate; now the work of the soul has become subordinate and what was secondary is the chief work.'</q></p>
    <p>11. A brother questioned him saying, 'What is the work of the soul which we now consider to be subordinate, and what is that which was subordinate and which we now consider to be our chief work?' The old man said, <q who="m8">'Everything you do as a commandment of God is the work of the soul; but to work and to gather goods together for a personal motive ought to be held as subordinate.'</q> Then the brother said, 'Explain this matter to me.' So the old man said,<q who="m8"> 'Suppose you hear it said that I am ill and you ought to visit me; you say to yourself, "Shall I leave my work and go now? I had better finish my work and then go." Then another idea comes along and perhaps you never go; or again, another brother says to you, "Lend me a hand, brother"; and you say, "Shall I leave my own work and go and work with him? If you do not go, you are disregarding the commandment of God which is the work of the soul, and doing the work of your hands which is subordinate.'</q></p>
        <p>12. Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore of Pherme</persName> said, 'The man who remains standing when he repents, has not kept the commandment.'</p>
    <p>13. He also said, <q who="m8">'There is no other virtue than that of not being scornful.'</q></p>
    <p>14. He also said, <q who="m8">'The man who has learnt the sweetness of the cell flees from his neighbour but not as though he despised him.'</q></p>
    <p>15. He also said, <q who="m8">'If I do not cut myself off from these feelings of compassion, they will not let me be a monk.'</q></p>
    <p>16. He also said, <q who="m8">'In these days many take their rest before God gives it them.'</q></p>
    <p>17. He also said, <q who="m8">'Do not sleep in a place where there is a woman.'</q></p>
        <p>18. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName>, 'I wish to fulfil the commandments.' The old man told him that Abba Theonas had said to him, 'I want to fill my spirit with God.' Taking some flour to the bakery, he had made loaves which he gave to the poor who asked him for them; others asked for more, and he gave them the baskets, then the cloak he was wearing, and he came back to his cell with his loins girded with his cape. Afterwards he took himself to task telling himself that he had still not fulfilled the commandment of God.'</p>
    <p>19. Once when Abba Joseph was ill, he sent someone to say to Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName>, 'Come here, that I may see you before I leave the body.' It was the middle of the week and he did not go, but sent to say to him, 'If you wait until Saturday, I shall come; but if you depart, we shall see one another in the world to come.'</p>
    <p>20. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName>, 'Speak a word to me, for I am perishing,' and sorrowfully he said to him. <q who="m8">'I am myself in danger, so what can I say to you?'</q></p>
    <p>21. A brother came to see Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> to learn weaving from him. He took a rope with him. The old man said to him, <q who="m8">'Go, and come back early tomorrow.'</q> Getting up, the old man steeped the rope and prepared what was necessary, saying, <q who="m8">'Work in such and such a way,'</q> and he left him. Then he went back to his cell and sat down. When the time came he gave the brother something to eat and sent him away. The brother returned in the small hours and the old man said to him, <q who="m8">'Pick up your rope and take it away, for you have come to cast me into temptation and trouble.'</q> So he did not let him come in any more.</p>
    <p> 22. Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName>'s disciple said, 'Someone came today to sell some onions and he filled a basin with them for me. The old man said, <q who="m8">'Fill one with wheat and give it to him.'</q> There were two heaps of wheat, one of good wheat, the other of unsorted wheat. I filled him a basin of the unsorted wheat. Then the old man looked at me with anger and sorrow, and from fear, I fell down on the ground and broke the basin. When I made a prostration before him the old man said, <q who="m8">'Get up, it is not your fault but mine, because of what I said to you.'</q> Then he went and filled his lap with good wheat and gave it to the tradesman with the onions.</p>
    <p>23. One day Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> went to draw water with <persName ref="a15">a brother</persName>. The brother going ahead, saw a dragon in the lake. The old man said to him, '<q who="m8">Go, and walk on his head.'</q> But he was afraid and did not go. So the old man went. The beast saw him and fled away into the desert, as if it was ashamed.</p>
    <p>24. Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> was asked, 'If there was a sudden catastro- phe, would you be frightened, abba?' The old man replied, <q who="m8">'Even if the heavens and the earth were to collide, Theodore would not be frightened.'</q> He had prayed God to take away fear from him and it was because of this that he was questioned.</p>
    <p>25. It was said about him that, though he was made a deacon at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, he refused to exercise the office and fled to many places from it. Each time the old men brought him back to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, saying, 'Do not leave your deaconate.' Abba Theodore said to them, <q who="m8">'Let me pray God that he may tell me for certain whether I ought to take my part in the liturgy.'</q> Then he prayed God in this manner, <q who="m8">'If it is your will that I should stand in this place, make me certain of it.'</q> Then appeared to him a column of fire, reaching from earth to heaven, and a voice said to him, 'If you can become like this pillar,
        go, be a deacon.' On hearing this he decided never to accept the office. When he went to church the brethren bowed before him saying, 'If you do not wish to be deacon, at least hold the chalice.' But he refused, saying, <q who="m8">'If you do not leave me alone, I shall leave this place.'</q> So they left him in peace.</p>
    <listEvent>
        <event><desc>Theodore traveled to and often fled from Scetis</desc></event> 
        <listRelation><relation type="travled-to" name="traveler" active="m8" passive="p1">
            <desc>lived in
                <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>
            </desc></relation>
        </listRelation>
    </listEvent>
        <p>26. It was said of him, that when <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> was laid waste, he went to live in Pherme. When he grew old he was ill. So he was brought food. Whatever the first one brought him, he gave to the second,
        and so on; what he received from the first, he offered to the next. When the time to eat came, he ate what the one who came then brought him.</p>
    <p> 27. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore</persName> that when he settled down at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, a demon came to him wanting to enter his cell, but he bound him to the outside of his cell. Once more another demon tried to enter, and he bound him too. A third demon came as well, and finding the other two bound, said to them, <q who="m8">'Why are you standing outside like this?'</q> They said to him, 'He is sitting inside, and will not let us enter.' So the demon tried to enter by force. The old man bound him too. Fearing the prayers of the old man, they begged him, saying, 'Let us go,' and the old man said to them, <q who="m8">'Go away.'</q> Then they went off covered with confusion.</p>
    <listEvent>
        <event><desc>Theodore lived in Scetis</desc></event> 
        <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m8" passive="p1">
            <desc>lived in
                <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>
            </desc></relation>
        </listRelation>
    </listEvent>
    <p> 28. One of the Fathers told this about Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore of Pherme</persName>: 'One evening I came to him and found him wearing a torn habit, his chest bare and his cowl hanging in front of it. Now it happened that a great man came to see him. When he had knocked, the old man went to open the door, and having met him, sat down at the door to talk with him. Then I took one side of his cape and covered his shoulders with it. But the old man put out his hand and snatched it off. When the great man had gone, I said to him, 'Abba, why did you do that? This man came to be edified, perhaps he will be shocked.' Then the old man said to me, <q who="m8">'What do you mean, abba? Are we still the slaves of men? We did what was necessary, the rest is superfluous. He who wishes to be edified, let him be edified; he who wishes to be shocked, let him be shocked; as for me, I meet people as they find me.'</q> Then he said to his disciple, <q who="m8">'If someone comes to see me, do not say anything out of human respect, but if I am eating, say to him, "He is eating"; and if I am sleeping, say to him, "He is sleeping."'</q></p>
    <p>  29. Three thieves came to him one day and while the first two held him, the third took away his property. When he had taken the books, he wanted to take the habit as well. So he said to them, <q who="m8">'Leave that.'</q> But they did not agree. So, fighting with his hands he pushed them both away. Seeing this, they were very frightened. Then the old man said to them, <q who="m8">'Do not fear; divide these things into four parts: take three and leave me one.'</q> So they did this and in his part he got the habit which he used for the synaxis.</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Theodore of Enaton">
    <p>1. Abba <persName ref="m9">Theodore of Enaton</persName> said,<q who="m9"> 'When I was young, I lived in the desert. One day I went to the bakery to make two loaves, and there I found a brother also wanting to make bread, but there was no-one to help him. So I put mine on one side, to lend him a hand. When the work was done, another brother came, and again I lent him a hand in cooking his food. Then a third came, and I did the same; and similarly one after the other, I baked for each of those who came. I made six batches. Later I made my own two loaves, since no-one else came.'</q></p>
    <p>2. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m9">Theodore</persName> and Abba <persName ref="m19">Lucius</persName> of Enaton that they spent fifty years mocking their temptations by saying, <q who="m9">'After this winter, we will leave here.'</q> When the summer came, they said, <q who="m9">'After this summer, we will go away from here.'</q> They passed all their lives in this way, these Fathers whose memory we should always preserve.</p>
    <p>3. Abba <persName ref="m9">Theodore of Enaton</persName> said, <q who="m9">'If God reproaches us for carelessness in our prayers and infidelities in our psalmody, we cannot be saved.'</q>  
    </p>
</div> 
<div type="section" n="Theodore of Eleutheropolis">
    <p> 1. Abba <persName ref="m29">Abraham of <placeName ref="p6">Iberia<geo>41.836468 44.6891385</geo></placeName></persName> asked Abba <persName ref="m10">Theodore of <placeName ref="p7">Eleutheropolis<geo>31.6123197 34.8919445667</geo></placeName></persName>, <q who="m29">'Father, which is right? Ought I to seek glory for myself, or ignominy?'</q> The old man said, <q who="m10">'As far as I am concerned, I prefer to seek glory rather than ignominy. If I do something good, and praise myself for it, I can condemn my thoughts by saying to myself that I do not deserve the praise; but ignominy comes from evil deeds. How then can I appease my conscience if men have been shocked because of me? It is better, therefore, to do good and praise oneself for it.'</q> Abba Abraham said, <q who="m29">'Father, you have spoken well.'</q>
        <listPerson>
            <person><persName ref="m10"></persName></person>
            <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m10" passive="m29"/></listRelation>
        </listPerson>
        <listEvent><event><desc>Abraham lived in Iberia</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m29" passive="p6">
                <desc>in
                    <placeName ref="p6">Iberia<geo>41.836468 44.6891385</geo></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
        <listEvent><event><desc>Theodore lived in Eleutheropolis</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m10" passive="p7">
                <desc>in
                    <placeName ref="p7">Eleutheropolis<geo>31.6123197 34.8919445667</geo></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
    </p>
    <p> 2. Abba <persName ref="m10">Theodore</persName> said, <q who="m10">'Privation of food mortifies the body of the monk.'</q> <persName ref="a10">Another old man</persName> said, <q who="a10">'Vigils mortify it still more.'</q>
        <listPerson>
        <person><persName ref="m10"></persName></person>
        <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="m10" passive="a10"/></listRelation>
    </listPerson></p>
        <p>3. Abba <persName ref="m10">Theodore</persName> also said, '<q who="m10">If you are temperate, do not judge the fornicator, for you would then transgress the law just as much. And he who said, "Do not commit formication," also said, "Do not judge." '</q> </p>
</div>           
<div type="section" n="Theophilus the Archbishop">
       <p> 1. One day blessed <persName ref="m11">Theophilus</persName> the archbishop came to the mountain of Nitria and the abba of the mountain came to meet him. The archbishop said to him, 'Father, in this way of life which you follow, what do you find to be best?' The old man said to him, 'The act of accusing myself, and of constantly reproaching myself to myself.' Abba <persName ref="m11">Theophilus</persName> said to him, 'There is no other way but
        this.'</p>
        <p>2. The same Abba <persName ref="m11">Theophilus</persName>, the archbishop, came to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> one day. The brethren who were assembled said to Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName>, 'Say something to the archbishop, so that he may be edified.' The old man said to them, 'If he is not edified by my silence, he will not be edified by my speech.'</p>
       <p> 3. <persName ref="m11">Theophilus</persName> the archbishop summoned some Fathers to go to Alexandria one day, to pray and to destroy the heathen temples there. As they were eating with him, they were brought some veal for food and they ate it without realising what it was. The bishop, taking a piece of meat, offered it to the old man beside him, saying, 'Here is a nice piece of meat, abba, eat it.' But he replied, 'Till this moment, we believed we were eating vegetables, but if it is meat, we do not eat it.' None of them tasted any more of the meat which was brought.</p>
       <p> 4. The same Abba <persName ref="m11">Theophilus</persName> said, 'What fear, what trembling, what uneasiness will there be for us when our soul is separated from the body. Then indeed the force and strength of the adverse powers come against us, the rulers of darkness, those who command the world of evil, the principalities, the powers, the spirits of evil. They accuse our souls as in a lawsuit, bringing before it all the sins it has committed, whether deliberately or through ignorance, from its youth until the time when it has been taken away. So they stand accusing it of all it has done. Furthermore, what anxiety do you suppose the soul will have at that hour, until sentence is pronounced and it gains its liberty. That is its hour of affliction, until it sees what will happen to it. On the other hand, the divine powers stand on the opposite side, and they present the good deeds of the soul. Consider the fear and trembling of the soul standing between them until in judgement it receives the sentence of the righteous judge. If it is judged worthy, the demons will receive their punishment, and it will be carried away by the angels. Then thereafter you will be without disquiet, or rather you will live according to that which is written: "Even as the habitation of those who rejoice is in you." (Ps. 87.7) Then will the Scripture be fulfilled: "Sorrow and sighing shall flee away." (Isaiah 35.10)
        'Then your liberated soul will go on to that joy and ineffable glory in which it will be established. But if it is found to have lived carelessly, it will hear that terrible voice: "Take away the ungodly, that he may not see the glory of the Lord." (cf. Isaiah 26.10) Then the day of anger, the day of affliction, the day of darkness and shadow seizes upon it. Abandoned to outer darkness and con- demned to everlasting fire it will be punished through the ages without end. Where then is the vanity of the world? Where is vain-glory? Where is carnal life? Where is enjoyment? Where is imagination? Where is ease? Where is boasting? Riches? Nobility? Father, mother, brother? Who could take the soul out of its pains when it is burning in the fire, and remove it from bitter torments?
        'Since this is so, in what manner ought we not to give ourselves to holy and devout works? What love ought we to acquire? What manner of life? What virtues? What speed? What diligence? What prayer? What prudence? Scripture says: "In this waiting, let us make every effort to be found blameless and without reproach in peace." (cf. I Cor. 1.7-8) In this way, we shall be worthy to hear it said: "Come, O blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom pre- pared for you from the foundation of the world." (Matt. 25.34) Amen.'</p>
       <p> 5. The same Abba <persName ref="m11">Theophilus</persName>, the archbishop, at the point of death, said, 'You are blessed, Abba <persName ref="m28">Arsenius</persName>, because you have always had this hour in mind.'
</p>
    
</div>
<div type="section" n="John the Cenobite">
    <p>
        1. A brother lived in a cenobium and he was a very vigorous ascetic. Some brothers who had heard about him in <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, came to see him. They entered the place where he was working. He greeted them, and turning round, went back to his work. When they saw what he was doing, the brethren said to him, '<persName ref="m12">John</persName>, who clothed you in the habit? Who made you a monk? Have you not been taught to take the sheepskin from the brothers and to say to them, let us pray; or perhaps, sit down.' He said to them, 'John, the sinner, has no time to attend to that.'
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Isidore the Priest">
        <p>1. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName>, priest of <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, that when anyone had a brother who was sick, or careless or irritable, and wanted to send him away, he said, 'Bring him here to me.' Then he took charge of him and by his long-suffering he cured him.</p>
       <p> 2. A brother asked him, 'Why are the demons so frightened of you?' The old man said to him, 'Because I have practised asceticism since the day I became a monk, and not allowed anger to reach my
        lips.'</p>
        <p>3. He also said that for forty years he had been tempted to sin in thought but that he had never consented either to covetousness or to anger.</p>
       <p> 4. He also said, 'When I was younger and remained in my cell I set no limit to prayer; the night was for me as much the time of prayer as the day.'</p>
        <p>5. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> used to say this about Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName>: every night he plaited a bundle of palms, and the brethren pleaded with him saying, 'Rest a little, for you are getting old.' But he said to them, 'Even if <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName> were burned, and his ashes thrown to the winds, I would not allow myself any relaxation because the Son of God came here for our sake.'</p>
        <p>6. The same abba said concerning Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName> that his thoughts said to him, 'You are a great man.' He said to them, 'Am I to be compared with Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName>; am I become like Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName>, or like the other Fathers who pleased God?' When he said this he was at peace. When the demons who are at war with men tried to make him afraid, suggesting that, after all this, he would still go to hell, he replied, 'Even if I am sent there, I shall find you beneath me.'</p>
        <p>7. Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName> said, 'One day I went to the market place to sell some small goods; when I saw anger approaching me, I left the things and fled.'</p>
        <p>8. Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName> went one day to see Abba <persName ref="m11">Theophilus</persName>, arch- bishop of Alexandria and when he returned to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> the brethren asked him, 'What is going on in the city?' But he said to them, 'Truly, brothers, I did not see the face of anyone there, except that of the archbishop.' Hearing this they were very anxious and said to him, 'Has there been a disaster there, then, abba?' He said, 'Not at all, but the thought of looking at anyone did not get the better of me.' At these words they were filled with admiration, and strengthened in their intention of guarding the eyes from all distrac- tion.</p>
      <p>  9. The same Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName> said, 'It is the wisdom of the saints to recognize the will of God. Indeed, in obeying the truth, man surpasses everything else, for he is the image and likeness of God. Of all evil suggestions, the most terrible is that of following one's own heart, that is to say, one's own thought, and not the law of God. A man who does this will be afflicted later on, because he has not recognized the mystery, and he has not found the way of the saints in order to work in it. For now is the time to labour for the Lord, for salvation is found in the day of affliction: for it is written: "By your endurance you will gain your lives." ' (Luke 21.19)</p>
        <p>10. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> also said about Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName> that wherever he addressed the brothers in church he said only one thing, 'Forgive your brother, so that you also may be forgiven.'</p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Joseph of Panephysis">
    <p>
        I . Some Fathers went to Panephysis to see Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName> and ask him what kind of reception they should give to the brethren to whom they gave lodging, whether they ought to mix with them and speak freely with them. Before they asked him, the old man said to his disciple, 'Consider what I am going to do today, and remain still.' Then the old man put two mats, one on his right and one on his left and said, 'Sit down.' Then he went inside his cell and put on beggar's garments. Then he came out again and walked in between them. After this, he went back to put on his own clothes again; coming out once more, he sat down between them. They were surprised at the things he did. So he said to them: 'Have you considered what I have done?' They replied that they had. 'Was I changed by those contemptible garments?' They said 'No.' Then he said to them: 'I remained the same, then, in both sets of clothes, the former did not change me and the latter have not done me harm. This is how we ought to behave when we receive visiting brethren, according to the holy Gospel which says, "Render to Caesar the things which are Caesar's and to God the things which are God's." (Matt. 22.21) So when brothers come, let us receive them and speak freely with them. On the other hand, when we are alone we ought to weep, in order that we may persevere.' At these words the visitors were filled with astonishment because he had answered what they had in their hearts even before they had asked him and they gave glory to God.
        2. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName>, 'Tell me how to become a monk.' He said, 'If you want to find rest here below, and hereafter, in all circumstances say, Who am I? and do not judge anyone.'
        3. The same abba asked Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName> another question saying, 'What should I do when the passions attack me? Should I resist them, or let them enter?' The old man said to him, 'Let them enter and fight against them.' So he returned to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> where he remained. Now someone from Thebes came to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> and said to the brethren, 'I asked Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName> if I ought to resist the passions when they approach, or let them enter and he replied I ought not to allow them the smallest entry but cut them off immediately.' When Abba Poe- men learned that Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName> had spoken to the brother from Thebes in this way, he got up and went to see him at Panephysis and said, 'Abba, I consulted you about my thoughts and you have said one thing to me, and another to the Theban.' The old man said
        to him, 'Do you not know that I love you?' He said, 'Yes.' 'And did you not say to me: speak to me as you speak to yourself?' 'That is right.' Then the old man said, 'Truly, if the passions enter you and you fight them you become stronger. I spoke to you as to myself. But there are others who cannot profit in this way if the passions approach them, and so they must cut them off immediately.'
        4. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName>, saying, 'What should I do, for I do not have the strength to bear evil, nor to work for charity's sake?' The old man said to him, 'If you cannot do any of these
        things, at least guard your conscience from all evil with regard to
        your neighbour and you will be saved.'
        5. One of the brethren related this, 'One day I went to lower Heracliopolis to see Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName>. Now in the monastery there was a very good mulberry tree. At early dawn he said to me, 'Go and eat.' But as it was Friday I did not go, because of the fast; so I asked him, 'For God's sake, explain this to me. Here you are saying to me, go and eat but I did not go, because of the fast. I blushed for shame thinking of your command. I asked myself what was the old man's intention in saying that and I wondered if I ought to have done it, since he told me to.' The old man said, 'At the beginning the Fathers do not speak to the brothers as they ought to do, but rather in an ambiguous manner, and if they see that they do what is right, then they no longer speak like that, but tell them the truth when they know they are obedient in all things.'
        6. Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName> said to Abba Lot, 'You cannot be a monk unless you become like a consuming fire.'
        7. Abba Lot went to see Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName> and said to him, 'Abba, as far as I can I say my little office, I fast a little, I pray and meditate, I live in peace and as far as I can, I purify my thoughts. What else can I do?' Then the old man stood up and stretched his hands towards heaven. His fingers became like ten lamps of fire and he said to him, 'If you will, you can become all flame.'
        8. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName> this, 'I want to leave the monas- tery, and live as a solitary.' The old man said to him, 'Go wherever you find your soul is most at peace, and stay there, without blame.' The brother said to him, 'But I am at peace both in the monastery and in the solitary life; will you tell me what to do?' The Old man said to him, 'If you are at peace both in the monastery and in the solitary life, put these two thoughts as it were in the balance and wherever you see your thoughts will profit most and make progress, that is what you should do.'
        9. One of the old men joined one of his companions and went with him to visit Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName>. He said to him, 'Tell your disciple to saddle the ass.' The other replied, 'Call him, and he will do whatever you want.' 'What is his name?' 'I do not know.' 'How long has he been with you, and you do not know his.name?' He replied, 'For two years.' The other said, 'If in two years you have not learnt your disciple's name, do I need to know it for a single day?'
        10. Some brothers happened one day to meet at Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName>'s cell. While they were sitting there, questioning him, he became cheerful and, filled with happiness he said to them, 'I am a king today, for I reign over the passions.'
        11. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m14">Joseph</persName> of Panephysis that when he was at the point of death, while some old men were seated round him, he looked towards the window and saw the devil sitting close to it. Then calling his disciple he said to him, 'Bring my stick, for there is one there who thinks I am getting old and have no more strength against him.' As he gripped his stick the old men saw that the devil fled through the window like a dog, and disappeared from sight.
        
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="John the Persian">
    <p>
        1. A demoniac boy came one day to be healed, and some brothers from an Egyptian monastery arrived. As one old man was coming out to meet them he saw a brother sinning with the boy, but he did not accuse him; he said, 'If God who has made them sees them and does not burn them, who am I to blame them?'
        2. One of the Fathers related of Abba <persName ref="m15">John</persName> the Persian that his great charity had brought him to a profound innocence. He dwelt in Arabia of <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName>. One day he borrowed some money from a brother and bought some flax for his work. Then a brother came and asked him, 'Abba, give me a little flax so that I can make myself a cloak.' He gave him some readily. Similarly, another brother came and asked him, 'Give me a little flax, so that I can make some cloth.' So he gave him some too. Others came and asked him for things and he simply gave them cheerfully. Later, the owner of the money came to reclaim it. The old man said to him, 'I will go and get it for you.' Because he could not return it to him, he went to Abba James, who was a deacon, to ask him to give him some money so that he could return it to the brother. On the way he found a coin    
        on the ground but he did not touch it. He said a prayer and returned to his cell. But the brother came once more pestering him about the money, and the old man said to him, 'I am very worried about it.' Once again he went, found the coin on the ground where it was lying and once again he said a prayer and returned to his cell. But the brother came back to pester him as before. The old man said to him, 'This time I will certainly bring it to you.' Once again he got up and went to the place where the coin lay on the ground. He said a prayer and went to tell Abba James, 'Abba, as I was coming here, I found this coin on the road. Please make it known in the neighbourhood, in case someone has lost it; and if its owner is found, give it him.' So the old man went and asked about it for three days, but no one who had lost a piece of money came. Then the old man said to Abba James, 'Then if no-one has lost it, give it to this brother, for I owe it him. As I was coming to ask you for alms in order to give him his due, I found it.' The old man was astonished that, having a debt and finding that piece, he had not picked it up at once and given it to him. It was equally to his credit that when someone came to borrow something from Abba <persName ref="m15">John</persName>, he did not give it him himself, but said to the brother, 'Go and help yourself to whatever you need,' and when someone brought anything back to him, he would say, 'Put it back where it belongs.' If the borrower did not return the thing he did not say anything to him.
        <listEvent>
            <event><desc>John the Persian lived in Egypt</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m15" passive="p8">
                <desc>lived in
                    <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13</geo></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
        3. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m15">John</persName> the Persian that when some evildoers came to him, he took a basin and wanted to wash their feet. But they were filled with confusion, and began to do penance.
        4. Someone said to Abba <persName ref="m15">John</persName> the Persian, 'We have borne great afflictions for the sake of the kingdom of heaven. Shall we inherit it?' The old man said, 'As for me, I am confident I shall obtain the inheritance of Jerusalem on high, which is written in the heavens. Why should I not be confident? I have been hospitable like Abraham, meek like Moses, holy like Aaron, patient like Job, hum- ble like David, a hermit like <persName ref="m15">John</persName>, filled with compunction like Jeremiah, a master like Paul, full of faith like Peter, wise like Solomon. Like the thief, I trust that he who of his natural goodness has given me all that, will also grant me the kingdom.'
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Hilarion">
    <p>
        1. From <placeName ref="p5">Palestine<geo>32.5  37.5</geo></placeName>, Abba <persName ref="m16">Hilarion</persName> went to the mountain to Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName>. Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> said to him, 'You are welcome, torch which awakens the day.' Abba <persName ref="m16">Hilarion</persName> said, 'Peace to you, pillar of light, giving light to the world.'    
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Cassian">
    <p>
        1. Abba <persName ref="m17">Cassian</persName> related the following: 'The holy Germanus and I went to <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName>, to visit an old man. Because he offered us hospital- ity we asked him, "Why do you not keep the rule of fasting, when you receive visiting brothers, as we have received it in <placeName ref="p5">Palestine<geo>32.5  37.5</geo></placeName>?" He replied, "Fasting is always to hand but you I cannot have with me always. Furthermore, fasting is certainly a useful and necessary thing, but it depends on our choice while the law of God lays it upon us to do the works of charity. Thus receiving Christ in you, I ought to serve you will all diligence, but when I have taken leave of you, I can resume the rule of fasting again. For 'Can the wedding guests fast while the bridegroom is with them, but when the bride- groom is taken from them, then they will fast in that day.' " ' (Mark 2. 19-20)
        <listEvent>
            <event><desc>Cassian visited Egypt</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="visited" name="visitor" active="m17" passive="p8">
                <desc>lived in
                    <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13</geo></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
        2. The same abba said, 'There was an old man who was served by a holy virgin and men said he was not pure. The old man heard what was said. When he was on the point of dying he said to the Fathers, "When I am dead, plant my stick in the grave; if it grows and bears fruit, know that I am pure from all contact with her; but if it does not grow, know that I have sinned with her." So they planted the stick and on the third day it budded and bore fruit, and they all gave glory to God.'
        3. He also said, 'We went to see another old man who made us eat. Then when we had had enough, he pressed us to take some more food. When I said to him I could not take any more, he replied, "This is the sixth time I have set the table for the brothers who come, and inviting each of them, have eaten with him, and I am still hungry. But though you have eaten only once of this food, you are already satisfied, to the extent that you cannot eat any more."'
        4. The same Father related this: 'Abba John, abbot of a great monastery, went to Abba Paesius who had been living for forty years very far off in the desert. As he was very fond of him and could therefore speak freely with him, he said to him, "What good have you done by living here in retreat for so long, and not being easily disturbed by anyone?" He replied, "Since I lived in solitude the sun has never seen me eating." Abba John said to him, "As for me, it has never seen me angry." '
        5. The brothers surrounded the same Abba John who was at the point of death and ready to depart eagerly and joyously to God. They asked him to leave them a concise and salutary saying as their inheritance, which would enable them to become perfect in Christ. Groaning he said to them, 'I have never done my own will, nor taught anything which I had not previously carried out.'
        6. He related with regard to another old man living in the desert, that he had asked God to grant him never to become sleepy during a spiritual conference, but, if someone uttered slanderous or useless words, to be able to go to sleep at once, so that his ears should never be touched by that poison. This old man also said that the devil, enemy of all spiritual instruction, works hard to provoke useless words. He used the following example, 'Once when I was talking to some brothers on a helpful topic, they were overcome by sleep so deep, that they could not even move their eyelids any longer. Then, wishing to show them the power of the devil, I introduced a trivial subject of conversation. Immediately, they woke up, full of joy. Then I said to them with many sighs, "Until now, we were discussing heavenly things and your eyes were heavy with sleep, but when I embarked on a useless discourse, you all woke up with alacrity. Therefore, brothers, I implore you to recognize the power of the evil demon; pay attention to yourselves, and guard yourselves from the desire to sleep when you are doing or listening to some- thing spiritual."'
        7. He also said, 'There was a distinguished official who had re- nounced everything and distributed his goods to the poor. He kept a little bit for his personal use because he did not want to accept the humiliation that comes from total renunciation, nor did he sincerely want to submit to the rule of the monastery. Saint Basil said to him, "You have lost your senatorial rank without becoming a monk." '
        8. He also said, 'There was a monk living in a cave in the desert. His relations according to the flesh let him know, "Your father is very ill, at the point of death: come and receive his inheritance." He replied to them, "I died to the world before he did and the dead do not inherit from the living." '
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Cyrus">
    <p>
        1. Abba <persName ref="m18">Cyrus</persName> of Alexandria was asked about the temptation of fornication, and he replied, 'If you do not think about it, you have no hope, for if you are not thinking about it, you are doing it. I mean, he who does not fight against the sin and resist it in his spirit will commit the sin physically. It is very true that he who is fornicating in fact is not worried with thinking about it.' The old man questioned the brother, saying, 'Do you not usually talk to women?' The brother said, 'No; my thoughts are about old and new represen- tations of them: it is their remembrance which overcomes me.' The old man said to him, 'Do not fear the dead, but flee from the living, and before all things persist in prayer.'
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Lucius">
    <p>
        1. Some of the monks who are called Euchites went to Enaton to see Abba <persName ref="m19">Lucius</persName>. The old man asked them, 'What is your manual work?' They said, 'We do not touch manual work but as the Apostle says, we pray without ceasing.' The old man asked them if they did not eat and they replied they did. So he said to them, 'When you are eating, who prays for you then?' Again he asked them if they did not sleep and they replied they did. And he said to them, 'When you are asleep, who prays for you then?' They could not find any answer to give him. He said to them, 'Forgive me, but you do not act as you speak. I will show you how, while doing my manual work, I pray without interruption. I sit down with God, soaking my reeds and plaiting my ropes, and I say, "God, have mercy on me; according to your great goodness and according to the multi- tude of your mercies, save me from my sins." ' So he asked them if this were not prayer and they replied it was. Then he said to them, 'So when I have spent the whole day working and praying, making thirteen pieces of money more or less, I put two pieces of money outside the door and I pay for my food with the rest of the money. He who takes the two pieces of money prays for me when I am eating and when I am sleeping; so, by the grace of God, I fulfil the precept to pray without ceasing.'
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Longinus">
    <p>
        1. One day Abba <persName ref="m20">Longinus</persName> questioned Abba <persName ref="m19">Lucius</persName> about three thoughts saying first, 'I want to go into exile.' The old man said to him, 'If you cannot control your tongue, you will not be an exile anywhere. Therefore control your tongue here, and you will be an exile.' Next he said to him, 'I wish to fast.' The old man replied, 'Isaiah said, "If you bend your neck like a rope or a bulrush that is not the fast I will accept; but rather, control your evil thoughts." ' (of. Isaiah 58) He said to him the third time, 'I wish to flee from men.' The old man replied, 'If you have not first of all lived rightly with men, you will not be able to live rightly in solitude.'
        2. Abba <persName ref="m20">Longinus</persName> said, 'If ever you are ill, say to your body, "Be ill and die; if you ask me for food outside the agreed time, I will not bring you even your daily food any more."'
        3. A woman had an illness they call cancer of the breast; she had heard of Abba <persName ref="m20">Longinus</persName> and wanted to meet him. Now he lived at the ninth milestone from Alexandria. As the woman was looking for him, the blessed man happened to be collecting wood beside the sea. When she met him, she said to him, 'Abba, where does Abba Lon- ginus, the servant of God live?' not knowing that it was he. He said, 'Why are you looking for that old imposter? Do not go to see him, for he is a deceiver. What is the matter with you?' The woman showed him where she was suffering. He made the sign of the cross over the sore and sent her away saying, 'Go, and God will heal you, for <persName ref="m20">Longinus</persName> cannot help you at all.' The woman went away confi- dent in this saying, and she was healed on the spot. Later, telling others what had happened and mentioning the distinctive marks of the old man, she learned that it was Abba <persName ref="m20">Longinus</persName> himself.
        4. Another time, they brought him one possessed by a demon. He said to those who were escorting him: 'I can do nothing for you; but go instead to Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName>.' So Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName> began to put pressure onto the demon to cast it out. The demon began to cry out: 'Per- haps, Abba <persName ref="m5">Zeno</persName>, you think I am going away because of you; look, down there Abba <persName ref="m20">Longinus</persName> is praying, and challenging me and it is for fear of his prayers that I go away, for to you I would not even have given an answer.'
        5. Abba <persName ref="m20">Longinus</persName> said to Abba Acacius: 'A woman knows she has conceived when she no longer loses any blood. So it is with the soul, she knows she has conceived the Holy Spirit when the passions stop coming out of her. But as long as one is held back in the passions, how can one dare to believe one is sinless? Give blood and receive the Spirit.'
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Macarius the Great">
    <p>
        1. Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said this about himself: 'When I was young and was living in a cell in <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName>, they took me to make me a cleric in the village. Because I did not wish to receive this dignity, I fled to another place. Then a devout layman joined me; he sold my manual work for me and served me. Now it happened that a virgin in the village, under the weight of temptation, committed sin. When
        she became pregnant, they asked her who was to blame. She said, "The anchorite." Then they came to seize me, led me to the village and hung pots black with soot and various other things round my neck and led me through the village in all directions, beating me and saying, "This monk has denied our virgin, catch him, catch him," and they beat me almost to death. Then one of the old men came and said, "What are you doing, how long will you go on beating this strange monk?" The man who served me was walking behind me, full of shame, for they covered him with insults too, saying, "Look at this anchorite, for whom you stood surety; what has he done?" The girl's parents said, "Do not let him go till he has given a pledge that he will keep her." I spoke to my servant and he vouched for me. Going to my cell, I gave him all the baskets I had, saying, "Sell them, and give my wife something to eat." Then I said to myself, "<persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, you have found yourself a wife; you must work a little more in order to keep her." So I worked night and day and sent my work to her. But when the time came for the wretch to give birth, she remained in labour many days without bringing forth, and they said to her, "What is the matter?" She said, "I know what it is, it is because I slandered the anchorite, and accused him unjustly; it is not he who is to blame, but such and such a young man." Then the man who served me came to me full of joy saying, "The virgin could not give birth until she had said 'The anchorite had nothing to do with it, but I have lied about him.' The whole village wants to come here solemnly and do penance before you." But when I heard this, for fear people would disturb me, I got up and fled here to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>. That is the original reason why I came here.'
        a. One day <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Egyptian went from <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> to the mountain of Nitria for the offering of Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName>. The old men said to him, 'Father, say a word to the brethren.' He said, 'I have not yet become a monk myself, but I have seen monks. One day when I was sitting in my cell, my thoughts were troubling me, suggesting that I should go to the desert and see what I could see there. I remained for five years, fighting against this thought, saying, per- haps it comes from the demons. But since the thought persisted, I left for the desert. There I found a sheet of water and an island in the midst, and the animals of the desert came to drink there. In the midst of these animals I saw two naked men, and my body trembled, for I believed they were spirits. Seeing me shaking, they said to me, "Do not be afraid, for we are men." Then I said to them, "Where do you come from, and how did you come to this desert?" They said, "We come from a monastery and having agreed together, we came here forty years ago. One of us is an Egyptian and the other a Libyan." They questioned me and asked me, "How is the world? Is the water rising in due time? Is the world enjoying prosperity?" I replied it was, then I asked them, "How can I become a monk?" They said to me, "If you do not give up all that is in the world, you cannot become a monk." I said to them, "But I am weak, and I cannot do as you do." So they said to me: "If you cannot become like us, sit in your cell and weep for your sins." I asked them, "When the winter comes are you not frozen? And when the heat comes do not your bodies burn?" They said, "It is God who has made this way of life for us. We do not freeze in winter, and the summer does us no harm." That is why I said that I have not yet become a monk, but I have seen monks.'
        3. When Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> dwelt in the great desert, he was the only one living as an anchorite, but lower down there was another desert where several brothers dwelt. The old man was surveying the road when he saw Satan drawing near in the likeness of a man and he passed by his dwelling. He seemed to be wearing some kind of cotton garment, full of holes, and a small flask hung at each hole. The old man said to him, 'Where are you off to?' He said, 'I am going to stir up the memories of the brethren.' The old man said, 'And what is the purpose of these small flasks?' He replied, 'I am taking food for the brethren to taste.' The old man said, 'All those kinds?' He replied, 'Yes, for if a brother does not like one sort of food, I offer him another, and if he does not like the second any better, I offer him a third; and of all these varieties he will like one at least.' With these words he departed. The old man remained watching the road until he saw him coming back again. When the old man saw him, he said to him: 'Good health to you.' The other replied: 'How can I be in good health?' The old man asked him what he meant, and he replied, 'Because they all opposed me, and no one received me.' The old man said, 'Ah, you did not find any friends down there?' He replied, 'Yes, I have a monk who is a friend down there. He at least obeys me and when he sees me he changes like the wind.'
        The old man asked him the name of this monk. 'Theopemtus,' he replied. With these words he went away. Then Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> got up and went to the desert below his own. When they heard of it the brothers took branches of palm to go to meet him. Each one got ready, thinking that it was to him the old man was coming down. But he enquired which was the one on the mountain called Theo- pemptus, and when he had found out he went to his cell. Theo- pemptus received him with joy. When he was alone with him the old man asked him, 'How are you getting on?' Theopemptus re- plied, 'Thanks to your prayers, all goes well.' The old man asked: 'Do not your thoughts war against you?' He replied: 'Up to now, it is all right,' for he was afraid to admit anything. The old man said to him, 'See how many years I have lived as an ascetic, and am
        praised by all, and though I am old, the spirit of fornication troubles me.' Theopemptus said, 'Believe me, abba, it is the same with me.' The old man went on admitting that other thoughts still warred against him, until he had brought him to admit them about himself. Then he said, 'How do you fast?' He replied, 'Till the ninth hour.' 'Practise fasting a little later; meditate on the Gospel and the other Scriptures, and if an alien thought arises within you, never look at it but always look upwards, and the Lord will come at once to your help.' When he had given the brother this rule, the old man then returned to his solitude. He was watching the road once more when he saw the devil, to whom he said, 'Where are you going this time?' He replied, 'To arouse the memories of the brothers,' and he went away. When he came back the saint asked him, 'How are the broth- ers?' He replied that it had gone badly. The old man asked him why. He replied, 'They are all obdurate, and the worst is the one friend I had who used to obey me. I do not know what has changed him, but not only does he not obey me any more, but he has become the most obdurate of them all. So I have promised myself not to go down there again at least not for a long time from now.' When he had said this, he went away leaving the old man, and the saint
        returned to his cell.
        4. One day Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Great came to Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName>'s dwelling on the mountain. When he knocked on the door, <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> came out to him and said to him, 'Who are you?' He replied, 'I am <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>.' Then <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> went inside and shut the door leaving him there. Later, seeing his patience, he opened the door and re- ceived <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> with joy, saying to him, 'I have wanted to see you for a long time, having heard about you.' He rendered him all the duties of hospitality and made him rest for he was very tired. When evening came, Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> soaked some palm-leaves for himself, and Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said to him, 'Allow me to soak some for myself.' He replied: 'Do so.' Having made a large bundle, he soaked them. Then sitting down in the evening they spoke of the salvation of the soul, while they plaited the leaves. The rope which <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> was making hung down through the window in the cave. Going in early, blessed <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> saw the length of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>' rope and said, 'Great power comes out of these hands.'
        5. Concerning the devastation of <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said to the brethern, 'When you see a cell built close to the marsh, know that the devastation of <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> is near; when you see trees, know that it is at the doors; and when you see young children, take up your sheep-skins, and go away.'
        6. Again, wishing to comfort the brethren, he said, 'A mother came here with her little child, possessed with a devil, who said to his mother, "Get up, woman, let us go away from here." She replied, "I cannot walk any further," and the little child said to her, "I will carry you myself." I wondered at the devil's tricks and how eager he was to make them flee.'
        7. Abba Sisoes said, 'When I was at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> with <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, we went up, seven of us, to bring in the harvest. Now a widow cried out behind us and would not stop weeping. So the old man called the owner of the field and said to him, "What is the matter with the woman that she goes on weeping?" "It is because her husband re- ceived a deposit in trust from someone and he died suddenly with- out saying where he had hidden it, and the owner of the deposit wants to take her and her children and make slaves of them." The old man said to him, "Tell her to come to us, when we take our mid-day rest." The woman came, and the old man said to her, "Why are you weeping all the time like this?" She replied, "My husband who had received a deposit on trust from someone, has died and he did not say when he died, where he had put it." The old man said to her, "Come, show me where you have buried him." Taking the brethren with him, he went with her. When they had come to the place, the old man said to her, "Go away to your house." While the brethren prayed, the old man asked the dead man, "So and so, where have you put the deposit?" The corpse replied, "It is hidden in the house, at the foot of the bed." The old man said, "Rest again, until the day of resurrection." When they saw this, the brethren were filled with fear and threw themselves at his feet. But the old man said to them, "It is not for my sake that this has happened, for I am nothing, but it is because of the widow and the orphans that God has performed this miracle. This is what is remarkable, that God wants the soul to be without sin and grants it all it asks." He went to tell the widow where the deposit was. Taking it, she returned it to its owner and thus freed her children. All who heard this story gave glory to God.'
        8. Abba Peter said this about the holy <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>: 'One day he came to the cell of an anchorite who happened to be ill, and he asked him if he would take something to eat, though his cell was stripped bare. When the other replied, "Some sherbet," that courageous man did not hesitate, but went as far as Alexandria to fetch some for the sick man. The astonishing thing is that no-one knew about it.'
        9. He also said that when Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> received all the breth- ren in simplicity, some of them asked him why he mixed with them like this. He replied, 'For twelve years I served the Lord, so that he might grant me this gift, and do you all advise me to give it up?'
        10. They said about Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> that when he visited the brethren he laid this rule upon himself, 'If there is wine, drink some for the brethren's sake, but for each cup of wine, spend a day without drinking water.' So the brothers would offer him some refreshment, and the old man would accept it joyfully to mortify himself; but when his disciple got to know about it he said to the brethren, 'In the name of God, do not offer him any more, or he will go and kill himself in his cell.' When they heard that, the brethren did not offer him wine any more.
        11. When Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> was returning from the marsh to his cell one day carrying some palm-leaves, he met the devil on the road with a scythe. The latter struck at him as much as he pleased, but in vain, and he said to him, 'What is your power, <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, that makes me powerless against you? All that you do, I do, too; you fast, so do I; you keep vigil, and I do not sleep at all; in one thing only do you beat me.' Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> asked what that was. He said, 'Your humility. Because of that I can do nothing against you.'
        12. Some Fathers questioned Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Egyptian, 'Why is it that whether you eat, or whether you fast, your body is always emaciated?' The old man said to them, 'The little bit of wood that is used to poke the vinebranches when they are burning ends by being entirely burnt up by the fire; in the same way, man purifies his soul in the fear of God, and the fear of God burns up his body.'
        13. One day Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> went up from <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> to Terenuthis and went into the temple to sleep. Now there were some old coffins of the pagans there. Taking one, he put it under his head as a pillow. The devils, seeing his audacity, were filled with jealousy and to make him afraid they called out, as though addressing a woman, 'So and so, come to bath with us.' Another devil replied from beneath him, as though among the dead, 'I have a stranger on top of me, and I cannot come.' But the old man was not afraid. On the contrary, he knocked on the coffin with assurance, saying, 'Awake, and go into the darkness, if you can.' Hearing this, the devils began to cry out with all their might, 'You have overcome us.' Filled with confu- sion, they fled.
        14. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Egyptian that one day when he was going up from <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> with a load of baskets, he sat down, overcome with weariness and began to say to himself, 'My God, you know very well that I cannot go any further,' and imme- diately he found himself at the river.
        <listEvent>
            <event><desc>Macarius lived in Egypt</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="lived-in" name="resident" active="m21" passive="p8">
                <desc>lived in
                    <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13</geo></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
        15. A man of Egypt had a paralytic son. He brought him to the cell of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, and put him down at the door weeping and went a good distance away. The old man stooped down and saw the child, and said to him, 'Who brought you here?' He replied, 'My father threw me down here and went away.' Then the old man said to him, 'Get up, and go back to him.' The child was cured on the spot; he got up and rejoined his father and they returned to their own home.
        16. Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Great said to the brothers at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, when he dismissed the assembly, 'Flee, my brothers.' One of the old men asked him, 'Where could we flee to beyond this desert?' He put his finger on his lips and said, 'Flee that,' and he went into his cell, shut the door and sat down.
        17. The same Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said, 'If you reprove someone, you yourself get carried away by anger and you are satisfying your own passion; do not lose yourself, therefore, in order to save another.'
        18. The same Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> while he was in <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName> discovered a man who owned a beast of burden engaged in plundering <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>' goods. So he came up to the thief as if he was a stranger and he helped him to load the animal. He saw him off in great peace of soul, saying, 'We have brought nothing into this world, and we cannot take anything out of the world.' (1 Tim. 6.7) 'The Lord gave and the Lord has taken away; blessed be the name of the Lord.' (Job
        1.21)
        19. Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> was asked, 'How should one pray?' The old man said, 'There is no need at all to make long discourses; it is enough to stretch out one's hands and say, "Lord, as you will, and as you know, have mercy." And if the conflict grows fiercer say, "Lord, help!" He knows very well what we need and he shews us his mercy.'
        20. Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said, 'If slander has become to you the same as praise, poverty as riches, deprivation as abundance, you will not die. Indeed it is impossible for anyone who firmly believes, who labours with devotion, to fall into the impurity of the passions and be led astray by the demons.'
        21. It was said that two brothers at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> had fallen into sin and that Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> of Alexandria had excommunicated them. Some brethren came and told Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Great of <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName> about it. He said, 'It is not the brothers who are excommunicated; it is <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> (for he loved him).' Hearing that he had been excom- municated by the old man, Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> fled to the marsh. Then Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Great went out and found him eaten up by mosquitoes. He said to him, 'So you have excommunicated some brothers; and yet they live apart in the village. I myself have excommunicated you and like a pretty young girl to the utmost privacy of her chamber, you have fled here. I have summoned the two brothers, and have learnt from them what happened, and I have told them nothing has happened. Examine yourself, then, my brother, and see if you have not been the sport of the demons, for you have lacked perception in this matter. But repent of your fault.' Then the other asked him, 'Please give me a penance.' Faced with his humility, the old man said, 'Go, fast for three weeks, eating only once a week.' For it was his usual custom to fast for the whole week.
        22. Abba <persName ref="m30">Moses</persName> said to Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, 'I should like to live in quiet prayer and the brethren do not let me.' Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said to him, 'I see that you are a sensitive man and incapable of sending a brother away. Well, if you want to live in peace, go to the interior desert, to Petra, and there you will be at peace.' And so he found peace.
        23. A brother came to see Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Egyptian, and said to him, 'Abba, give me a word, that I may be saved.' So the old man said, 'Go to the cemetery and abuse the dead.' The brother went there, abused them and threw stones at them; then he returned and told the old man about it. The latter said to him, 'Didn't they say anything to you?' He replied, 'No.' The old man said, 'Go back tomorrow and praise them.' So the brother went away and praised them, calling them, 'Apostles, saints and righteous men.' He re- turned to the old man and said to him, 'I have complimented them.' And the old man said to him, 'Did they not answer you?' The brother said no. The old man said to him, 'You know how you insulted them and they did not reply, and how you praised them and they did not speak; so you too if you wish to be saved must do the same and become a dead man. Like the dead, take no account of either the scorn of men or their praises, and you can be saved.'
        24. One day when Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> was going down to <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName> with some brethren, he heard a boy saying to his mother, 'Mother, there is a rich man who likes me, but I detest him; and on the other hand, there is a poor man who hates me, and I love him.' Hearing these words, Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> marvelled. So the brethren said to him: 'What is this saying, abba, that makes you marvel?' The old man said to them, 'Truly, our Lord is rich and loves us, and we do not listen to him; while our enemy the devil is poor and hates us, but we love his impurity.'
        25. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> asked him weeping, 'Give me a word that I may be saved.' But the old man replied, 'What you are looking for has disappeared now from among monks.'
        26. One day Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> went to see Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName>. He spoke to him and then returned to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>. The Fathers came to meet him, and as they were speaking, the old man said to them, 'I said to Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> that we do not have an offering in our district.' But the Fathers began to speak of other things without asking him to tell them the old man's reply and he himself did not tell them. One of the Fathers said about this that when the Fathers see that the brethren fail to question them about something that would be use- ful, they ought to begin talking about it themselves; but if they are not urged on by the brethren, they should not say anymore about it, so that they shall not be found to have spoken without being asked, and to have said unnecessary words.
        27. Abba Isaiah questioned Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> saying, 'Give me a word.' The old man said to him, 'Flee from men,' Abba Isaiah said to him, 'What does it mean to flee from men?' The old man said, 'It means to sit in your cell and weep for your sins.'
        28. Abba Paphnutius, the disciple of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, said, 'I asked my Father to say a word to me and he replied, "Do no evil to anyone, and do not judge anyone. Observe this and you will be saved."'
        29. Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said, 'Do not sleep in the cell of a brother who has a bad reputation.'
        30. The brethren came one day to Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> and they found nothing in this cell except stagnant water. So they said to him, 'Abba, come up to the village, and we will get some clean water for you.' The old man said to them, 'Brothers, do you know so-and-so's bakery in the village?' and they said that they did. The old man said to them, 'I know it, too. Do you know so-and-so's field, where the river runs?' They said, 'Yes.' The old man said to them, 'I know it too. So when I want to, I can go there myself, without your help.'
        31. They said of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> that if a brother came to see him with fear, like someone coming to see a great and holy old man, he did not say anything to him. But if one of the brethren said to him, as though to humiliate him, 'Abba, when you were a camel-driver, and stole nitre and sold it again, did not the keepers beat you?' If someone talked to him like that he would talk to them with joy about whatever they asked him.
        32. They said of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Great that he became, as it is written, a god upon earth, because, just as God protects the world, so Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> would cover the faults which he saw, as though he did not see them; and those which he heard, as though he did not hear them.
        33. Abba Bitimius related that Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said this: 'When I was living at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, two young strangers came down there. One had a beard, the other was beginning to grow one. They came towards me saying: "Where is Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>' cell?" I said to them: "What do you want with him?" They replied, "We have heard tell of him and of <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> and we have come to see him." I said to them, "I am he." Then they bowed low to me and said, "We want to live here." Seeing that they were delicate and had been brought up in comfort, I said to them, "You cannot live here." The elder said, "If we cannot live here, we will go somewhere else." Then I said to myself, "Why chase them away and be a stumbling block to them? Suffering will make them go away of their own accord." So I said to them, "Come and make yourselves a cell, if you can." They said, "Show us a place, and we will make one." The old man gave them an axe, a basket full of bread and salt, and showed them a lump of rock, saying, "Cut out some stones here, and bring wood from the marsh, make a roof, and live here." He added, "I thought they would choose to go away, because of the hardship. But they asked me what work they should do here." I replied, "Rope-making." And I took some leaves from the marsh and showed them the rudiments of weaving and how to handle the reeds. I said to them, "Make some baskets, give them to the keepers, and they will bring you bread." Then I went away. But they, with patience, did all that I had told them and for three years they did not come to see me. Now I wrestled with my thoughts, thinking, "What is their way of life? Why do they not come to ask me about their thoughts? Those who live far off come to see me, but those who live quite close do not come. They do not go to anyone else either; they only go to church, in silence, to receive the oblation." I prayed to God, fasting the whole week, that he would show me their way of life. At the end of the week, I got up and went to visit them, to see how they were. When I knocked, they opened the door and greeted me in silence. Having prayed, I sat down. The elder made a sign to the younger to go out and he sat plaiting the rope, without saying anything. At the ninth hour, he knocked, and the younger one returned and made a little soup and set the table at a sign of his elder brother. He put three small loaves on it and stood in silence. As for me, I said, "Rise, and let us eat." We got up to eat and he brought a small water-bottle and we drank. When the evening came, they said to me, "Are you going away?" I replied, "No, I will sleep here." They spread a mat for me on one side, another for themselves in the opposite corner. They took off their girdles and cowls, and lay down together on the mat. When they were settled, I prayed God that he would show me their way of life. Then the roof opened and it became as light
        as day, but they did not see the light. When they thought I was asleep, the elder tapped the younger on the side and they got up, put on their girdles again and stretched their hands towards heaven. I could see them, but they could not see me. I saw the demons coming like flies upon the younger one, some sitting on his mouth and others on his eyes. I saw the angel of the Lord circling round about him with a fiery sword, chasing the demons far from him. But they could not come near the elder one. When early dawn came, they lay down and I made as though I had just woken up and they did the same. The elder simply said to me "Shall we recite the twelve psalms?" and I said to him, "Yes." The younger one chanted five psalms in groups of six verses and an alleluia and at each verse a tongue of flame came out of his mouth and ascended to heaven. Likewise with the elder, when he opened his mouth to chant it was
        like a column of fire which came forth and ascended up to heaven; in my turn, I recited a little by heart. As I went out, I said, "Pray for me." But they bowed without saying a word. So I learned that the first was a perfect man, but the enemy was still fighting against the younger. A few days later the elder brother fell asleep and three days afterwards, his younger brother died too.' When the Fathers came to see Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, he used to take them to their cell, and say, 'Come and see the place of martyrdom of the young strangers.'
        34. One day the old men of the mountain sent a delegation to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> to Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> with these words, 'Deign to visit us so that we may see you before you go to the Lord, otherwise all the people will be grieved.' So he came to the mountain and all the people gathered round him. The old men asked him to say a word to the brothers. When he heard this, he said, 'Let us weep, brothers, and let tears gush out of our eyes, before we go to that place where our tears shall burn our bodies.' They all wept, falling with their faces on the ground and saying, 'Father, pray for us.'
        35. Another time a demon approached Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> with a knife and wanted to cut his foot. But, because of his humility he could not do so, and he said to him, 'All that you have, we have also; you are distinguished from us only by humility; by that you get the better of us.'
        36. Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said, 'If we keep remembering the wrongs which men have done us, we destroy the power of the remembrance of God. But if we remind ourselves of the evil deeds of the demons, we shall be invulnerable.'
        37. Abba Paphnutius, the disciple of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, repeated this saying of the old man, 'When I was small with other children, I used to eat bilberries and they used to go and steal the little figs. As they were running away, they dropped one of the figs, and I picked it up and ate it. Every time I remember this, I sit down and weep.'
        38. Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said, 'Walking in the desert one day, I found the skull of a dead man, lying on the ground. As I was moving it with my stick, the skull spoke to me. I said to it, "Who are you?" The skull replied, "I was high priest of the idols and of the pagans who dwelt in this place; but you are <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, the Spirit-bearer. Whenever you take pity on those who are in torments, and pray for them, they feel a little respite." The old man said to him, "What is this alleviation, and what is this torment?" He said to him, "As far as the sky is removed from the earth, so great is the fire beneath us; we are ourselves standing in the midst of the fire, from the feet up
        to the head. It is not possible to see anyone face to face, but the face of one is fixed to the back of another. Yet when you pray for us, each of us can see the other's face a little. Such is our respite." The old man in tears said, "Alas the day when that man was born!" He said to the skull, "Are there any punishments which are more pain- ful than this?" The skull said to him, "There is a more grievous punishment down below us." The old man said, "Who are the people down there?" The skull said to him: "We have received a little mercy since we did not know God, but those who know God and denied Him are down below us." Then, picking up the skull, the old man buried it.'
        39. They said of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> the Egyptian that one day he went up from <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> to the mountain of Nitria. As he approached the place he told his disciple to go on ahead. When the latter had gone on ahead, he met a priest of the pagans. The brother shouted after him saying, 'Oh, oh, devil, where are you off to?' The priest turned back and beat him and left him half dead. Then picking up his stick, he fled. When he had gone a little further, Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> met him running and said to him, 'Greetings! Greetings, you weary man!' Quite astonished, the other came up to him and said, 'What good do you see in me, that you greet me in this way?' The old man said to him, 'I have seen you wearing yourself out without knowing that you are wearing yourself out in vain.' The other said to him, 'I have been touched by your greeting and I realize that you are on God's side. But another wicked monk who met me insulted me and I have given him blows enough for him to die of them.' The old man realized that he was referring to his disciple. Then the priest fell at his feet and said, 'I will not let you go till you have made me a monk.' When they came to the place where the brother was, they put him onto their shoulders and carried him to the church in the mountain. When the people saw the priest with <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> they were astonished and they made him a monk. Through him many pagans became Christians. So Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said, 'One evil word makes even the good evil, while one good word makes even the evil good.'
        40. They said of Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> that a thief went into his cell when he was away. <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> came back to his cell and found the thief loading his things onto a camel. So <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> went into the cell, picked up his things and helped him load them onto the camel.
        When the loading was finished, the thief began to beat the camel to make it get up but in vain. Seeing that it did not get up, Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> went inside his cell, found a small hoe there, picked it up and put it onto the camel saying, 'Brother, the camel wants to have this.' Then the old man kicked it, saying, 'Get up.' At once the camel got up and went forward a little, because of his command. Then it lay down again and refused to get up until it was completely un- loaded; and then it set off.
        41. Abba Aio questioned Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName>, and said: 'Give me a word.' Abba <persName ref="m21">Macarius</persName> said to him: 'Flee from men, stay in your cell, weep for your sins, do not take pleasure in the conversation of men, and you will be saved.'
        
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Matoes">
    <p>
        1. Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> said, 'I prefer a light and steady activity, to one that is painful at the beginning but is soon broken off.'
        2. He also said, 'The nearer a man draws to God, the more he sees himself a sinner. It was when Isaiah the prophet saw God, that he declared himself "a man of unclean lips."' (Is. 6.5)
        3. He also said, 'When I was young, I would say to myself: perhaps one day I shall do something good; but now that I am old, I see that there is nothing good about me.'
        4. He also said, 'Satan does not know by what passion the soul can be overcome. He sows, but without knowing if he will reap, sometimes thoughts of fornication, sometimes thoughts of slander, and similarly for the other passions. He supplies nourishment to the passion which he sees the soul is slipping towards.'
        5. A brother went to Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> and said to him, 'How is it that the monks of <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> did more than the Scriptures required in loving their enemies more than themselves?' Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> said to him, 'As for me I have not yet managed to love those who love me as I love myself.'
        6. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName>, 'What ought I to do when a brother comes to see me and it is a fast day, or in the morning? This worries me.' The old man said to him, 'If you don't fuss about it and simply eat with the brother, that is all right, but if you are not expecting anyone and you eat, that is your own will.'
        7. Abba James said that he went to Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName>' cell and when he left he said to him, 'I want to go to the Cells.' He said to me: 'Greet Abba John for me.' So going to Abba John's cell I said to him, 'Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> greets you.' The old man said to me, 'Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> is an Israelite indeed in whom there is no guile.' A year later I returned to Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> and gave him Abba John's greeting. The old man said: 'I am not worthy of what the old man said, but know this: whenever you hear an old man praising his neighbour more than himself, it is because he has reached a great stature: for this is perfection to praise one's neighbour more than oneself.'
        8. Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> said, 'A brother came to me and said, "Slander is worse than fornication." I said to him, "That is a hard saying." He said to me, "What do you mean?" I said to him, "Slander is bad, but it is soon healed, for he who slanders often repents, saying that he has spoken unkindly; but fornication is physical death."'
        9. One day Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> went to Rhaithou, in the region of Magdolos. A brother went with him, and the bishop seized the old man and made him a priest. While they were eating together the bishop said, 'Forgive me, abba; I know you did not want it but it was in order that I might be blessed by you that I dared to do it.' The old man said humbly to him, 'I did not wish it, to be sure; but what really troubles me is that I must be separated from the brother who is with me and I am not able to keep on saying the prayers quite alone.' The bishop said to him, 'If you know that he is worthy, I will ordain him too.' Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> said, 'I do not know if he is worthy of it; I know only one thing, that he is better than I.' So the bishop ordained him also. Both of them died without having ap- proached the sanctuary to make the offering. The old man used to say, 'I have confidence in God that I shall not suffer great con- demnation through the laying on of hands since I do not make the offering. For the laying on of hands is for those who are without reproach.'
        10. Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> said that three old men went to Abba Paph- nutius, he who is called Cephalus, to ask a word of him. The old man said to them, 'What do you want me to say to you? A spiritual word, or a bodily word?' They said, 'A spiritual word.' The old man said to them, 'Go, and choose trials rather than quietness, dishonour rather than glory, and to give rather than to receive.'
        11. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> saying, 'Give me a word.' He said to him, 'Go, and pray God to put compunction in your heart, and give you humility; be aware of your faults; do not judge others but put yourself below everyone; do not be friendly with a boy nor with an heretical friend; put freedom of speech far from you; control your tongue and your belly; drink only a small quan- tity of wine, and if someone speaks about some topic, do not argue with him but if he is right, say, "Yes"; if he is wrong, say, "You know what you are saying," and do not argue with him about what he has said. That is humility.'
        12. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName>, 'Give me a word.' He said to him, 'Restrain the spirit of controversy in yourself in everything, and weep, have compunction, for the time is drawing near.'
        13. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m22">Matoes</persName> saying, 'What am I to do? My tongue makes me suffer, and every time I go among men, I cannot control it, but I condemn them in all the good they are doing and reproach them with it. What am I to do?' The old man replied, 'If you cannot contain yourself, flee into solitude. For this is a sickness. He who dwells with brethren must not be square, but round, so as to turn himself towards all.' He went on, 'It is not through virtue that I live in solitude, but through weakness; those who live in the midst of men are the strong ones.'
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Poemen"> <!-- his sayings make up 1/7 of the collection -->
    <p>
        1. While he was still young, Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> went one day to an old man to ask him about three thoughts. Having reached the old man, he forgot one of the three and went back to his cell. But as he was stretching out his hand to turn the key, he remembered the thought which he had forgotten and leaving the key, he returned to the old man. The old man said to him, 'You come quickly, brother.' He told him, 'At the moment when I was putting out my hand to grasp the key, I remembered the thought which I was trying to find; so I did not open the door, but have retraced my steps.' Now the length of the way was very great and the old man said to him, '<persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, Shepherd of the flock, your name will be known throughout <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName>.'
        2. Once Paesius, the brother of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, made friends with someone outside his cell. Now Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> did not want that. So he got up and fled to Abba Ammonas and said to him, 'Paesius, my brother, holds converse with someone, so I have no peace.' Abba Ammonas said to him, '<persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, are you still alive? Go, sit down in your cell; engrave it on your heart that you have been in the tomb for a year already.'
        3. One day the priests of the district came to the monasteries where Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> was. Abba Anoub came and said to him, 'Let us invite the priests in today.' But he stood for a long time without giving him any reply, and, quite offended, Abba Anoub went away. Those who were sitting beside <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'Abba, why didn't you answer him?' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to them, 'It is not my business, for I am dead and a dead man does not speak.'
        4. Before Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s group came there, there was an old man in <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName> who enjoyed considerable fame and repute. But when Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s group went up to <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, men left the old man to go to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> was grieved at this and said to his disciples, 'What is to be done about this great old man, for
        men grieve him by leaving him and coming to us who are nothing? What shall we do, then to comfort this old man?' He said to them, 'Make ready a little food, and take a skin of wine and let us go to see him and eat with him. And so we shall be able to comfort him.' So they put together some food, and went. When they knocked at the door the old man's disciple answered, saying, 'Who are you?' They responded, 'Tell the abba it is <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> who desires to be blessed by him.' The disciple reported this and the old man sent him to say, 'Go away, I have no time.' But in spite of the heat they persevered, saying, 'We shall not go away till we have been allowed to meet the old man.' Seeing their humility and patience, the old man was filled with compunction and opened the door to them. Then they went in and ate with him. During the meal he said, 'Truly, not only what I have heard about you is true, but I see that your works are a hundred-fold greater,' and from that day, he became their friend.
        5. One day the magistrate of that district wanted to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> but the old man did not want to see him. So, he seized his sister's son and threw him into prison, under the pretext that he was a criminal saying, 'If the old man comes to intercede for him I will let him go.' Then his sister came to weep at <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s door, but he gave her no answer. Then she reproached him in these words, saying, 'Heart of stone, have pity on me, for he is my only son.' But he only said to her, '<persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> has not brought forth any sons.' At that, she went away. When he heard this, the magistrate sent Poe- men this message, 'If you only ask me by a word, I will let him go.' The old man replied, 'Judge him according to the law; if he is worthy of death, put him to death, if not, do what you choose.'
        6. One day a brother sinned in a monastery. Now there was an anchorite in the district who had not gone out for a long time. The abba of the monastery went to see him and to give him the news that the brother had sinned. The anchorite said, 'Drive him away.' So the brother left the monastery and he went into a cave and wept there. Now it happened that some brothers were going to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and they heard him weeping. They entered, found him in great misery and invited him to go to see the old man, but he refused, saying, 'I am going to die here.' So when they reached Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s cell they told him about the brother. And he exhorted
        them, and he sent them away saying, 'Say to him, Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> sends for you.' Then the brother came. Seeing he was in such distress, Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> stood up, embraced him and was kind to him and invited him to eat. Then he sent one of the brethren to the anchorite, saying, 'For many years I have desired to see you, having heard of you. But because of our lethargy, we have not yet met. Now, however, if God wills it and you have the time, give yourself the trouble of coming here, and we will see one another.' The old man had never left his cell but when he heard this he said, 'If God had not inspired the old man, he would not have sent someone to summon me.' So he got up and went to see <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>. They embraced one another with joy and sat down. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'Two men dwelt in one place and someone belonging to each of them died; the first one, leaving his own dead, went to weep over the other's.' Hearing these words, the anchorite was filled with com- punction and he remembered what he had done and said, '<persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, you have gone up to heaven and I have gone down to the earth.'
        7. Many old men came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and one day it happened that a member of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s family came, who had a child whose face, through the power of the devil, was turned backwards. The father seeing the number of Fathers present, took the child and sat down outside the monastery, weeping. Now it happened that one of the old men came out and seeing him, asked him, 'Man, why are you weeping?' He replied, 'I am related to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, and see the misfortune which has overtaken my child. Though I want to bring him to the old man, we are afraid he does not want to see us. Each time he hears I am here, he has me driven away. But since you are with him, I have dared to come. If you will, Father, have pity on me, take the child inside and pray for him.' So the old man took the child, went inside and behaved with good sense. He did not immediately present him to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, but began with the lesser brethren, and said, 'Make the sign of the cross over this little child.' Having had him signed by all in turn, he presented him at last to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> did not want to make the sign of the cross over him, but the others urged him, saying, 'Do as everyone else has done.' So groaning he stood up and
        prayed, saying, 'God, heal your creature, that he be not ruled by the enemy.' When he had signed him, the child was healed immediately and given back whole to his father.
        8. A brother from Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s neighbourhood left to go to another country one day. There he met an anchorite. The latter was very charitable and many came to see him. The brother told him about Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>. When he heard of his virtue, the anchorite wanted to see him. Some time afterwards when the brother had returned to <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName> the anchorite went there to see the brother who had formerly paid him a visit. He had told him where he lived. When he saw him, the brother was astonished and very pleased. The anchorite said to him, 'Please will you be so kind as to take me to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>.' So he brought him to the old man and presented him, saying, 'This is a great man, full of charity, who is held in high estimation in his district. I have spoken to him about you, and he has come because he wants to see you.' So Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> received him with joy. They greeted one another and sat down. The visitor began to speak of the Scriptures, of spiritual and of heavenly things. But Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> turned his face away and answered nothing. Seeing that he did not speak to him, the other went away deeply grieved and said to the brother who had brought him, 'I have made this long journey in vain. For I have come to see the old man, and he does not wish to speak to me.' Then the brother went inside to
        Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and said to him, 'Abba, this great man who has so great a reputation in his own country has come here because of you. Why did you not speak to him?' The old man said, 'He is great and speaks of heavenly things and I am lowly and speak of earthly things. If he had spoken of the passions of the soul, I should have replied, but he speaks to me of spiritual things and I know nothing about that.' Then the brother came out and said to the visitor, 'The old man does not readily speak of the Scriptures, but if anyone consults him about the passions of the soul, he replies.' Filled with compunction, the visitor returned to the old man and said to him, 'What should I do, Abba, for the passions of the soul master me?' The old man turned towards him and replied joyfully, 'This time, you come as you should. Now open your mouth concerning this and I will fill it with good things.' Greatly edified, the other said to him, 'Truly, this is the right way!' He returned to his own country giving thanks to God that he had been counted worthy to meet so great a saint.
        9. One day the chief magistrate of the district seized one of the men of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s village, and everyone came to beg the old
        man to go and have him released. He replied, 'Leave me for three days and I will go.' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> prayed to the Lord in these words, 'Lord, do not give me this grace, otherwise they will never let me stay in this place.' Then the old man went to intercede with the magistrate, who replied, 'Will you intercede for a brigand, abba?' The old man rejoiced that he had not been granted this grace.
        10. They said that one day Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and his brethren were making ropes and the work was delayed because they had nothing with which to buy flax. One of their friends told a friendly mer- chant about this. Now Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> did not want to receive any- thing from anyone because of the trouble it causes. But the merchant wanted to do something for the old man, so he pretended to need ropes and brought a camel and took them away. When the brothers came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and learned what the merchant had done, they said, intending to praise him, 'Truly, Abba, he has taken them though he did not need them so as to do us a service.' Hearing that he had taken them without needing them, Abba Poe- men said to the brother, 'Get up, hire a camel and bring them back, and if you do not bring them back, <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> will no longer live here with you. I do not want to do wrong to someone who does not need those ropes, lest he should suffer loss by it and take my reward from me.' The brother went away with much labour and brought them back; otherwise the old man would have gone away from them. When he saw the ropes, he rejoiced as though he had found a great treasure.
        11. A priest of Pelusia heard it said of some brethren that they often went to the city, took baths and were careless in their behav- iour. He went to the synaxis, and took the habit away from them. Afterwards, his heart was moved, he repented and went to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, obsessed by his thoughts. He brought the monastic habits of the brothers and told him all about it. The old man said to him, 'Don't you sometimes have something of the old Adam in you?' The priest said, 'I have my share of the old Adam.' The abba said to him, 'Look, you are just like the brethren yourself; if you have even a little share of the old Adam, then you are subject to sin in the same way.' So the priest went and called the brothers and asked their pardon; and he clothed them in the monastic habit again and let them go.
        12. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'I have commit- ted a great sin and I want to do penance for three years.' The old man said to him, 'That is a lot.' The brother said, 'For one year?' The old man said again, 'That is a lot.' Those who were present said, 'For forty days?' He said again, 'That is a lot.' He added, 'I myself say that if a man repents with his whole heart and does not intend to commit the sin any more, God will accept him after only three days.'
        13. He also said, 'The distinctive mark of the monk is made clear through temptations.'
        14. He also said, 'Just as the king's body-guard stands always on guard at his side, so the soul should always be on guard against the demon of fornication.'
        15. Abba Anoub asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> about the impure thoughts which the heart of man brings forth and about vain desires. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'Is the axe any use without someone to cut with it? (Is. 10.15) If you do not make use of these thoughts, they will be ineffectual too.'
        16. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> also said, 'If Nabuzardan, the head-cook, had not come, the temple of the Lord would not have been burned: (2 Kings 24.8f.) that is to say: if slackness and greed did not come into the soul, the spirit would not be overcome in combat with the enemy.'
        17. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> that if he was invited to eat against his will, he wept but he went, so as not to refuse to obey his brother and cause him pain.
        18. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> also said, 'Do not live in a place where you see that some are jealous of you, for you will not make progress.'
        19. Some brothers told Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> of a brother who did not drink wine. He said, 'Wine is not for monks.'
        20. Abba Isaiah questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> on the subject of im- pure thoughts. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'It is like having a chest full of clothes, if one leaves them in disorder they are spoiled in the course of time. It is the same with thoughts. If we do not do
        anything about them, in time they are spoiled, that is to say, they
        disintegrate.'
        21. Abba Joseph put the same question and Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'If someone shuts a snake and a scorpion up in a bottle, in time they will be completely destroyed. So it is with evil thoughts: they are suggested by the demons; they disappear through pa- tience.'
        22. A brother came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and said to him, 'I sow my field and give away in charity what I reap from it.' The old man said to him, 'That is good,' and he departed with fervour and inten- sified his charity. Hearing this, Abba Anoub said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Do you not fear God, that you have spoken like that to the brother?' The old man remained silent. Two days later Abba Poe- men saw the brother coming and in the presence of Abba Anoub said to him, 'What did you ask me the other day? I was not attend- ing.' The brother said, 'I said that I sow my field and give away what I gain in charity.' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'I thought you were speaking of your brother who is in the world. If it is you who are doing this, it is not right for a monk.' At these words the brother was saddened and said, 'I do not know any other work and I cannot help sowing the fields.' When he had gone away, Abba Anoub made a prostration and said, 'Forgive me.' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'From the beginning I too knew it was not the work of a monk but I spoke as I did, adapting myself to his ideas and so I gave him courage to increase his charity. Now he has gone away full of grief and yet he will go on as before.'
        23. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'If a man has sinned and denies it, saying: "I have not sinned," do not reprimand him; for that will discourage him. But say to him, "Do not lose heart, brother, but be on guard in future," and you will stir his soul to repentance.'
        24. He also said, 'Experience is a good thing; it is that which tests a man.'
        25. He also said, 'A man who teaches without doing what he teaches is like a spring which cleanses and gives drink to everyone, but it not able to purify itself.'
        26. Going into <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName> one day, Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saw a woman who was sitting in a tomb and weeping bitterly. He said, 'If all the delights of the world were to come, they could not drive sorrow away from the soul of this woman. Even so the monk would always have compunction in himself.'
        <listEvent>
            <event><desc>Poemen traveled to Egypt</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="traveled-to" name="traveler" active="m23" passive="p8">
                <desc>traveled to
                    <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13</geo></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
        27. He also said, 'A man may seem to be silent, but if his heart is condemning others he is babbling ceaselessly. But there may be another who talks from morning till night and yet he is truly silent; that is, he says nothing that is not profitable.'
        28. A brother came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and said to him, 'Abba, I have many thoughts and they put me in danger.' The old man led him outside and said to him, 'Expand your chest and do not breathe in.' He said, 'I cannot do that.' Then the old man said to him, 'If you cannot do that, no more can you prevent thoughts from arising, but you can resist them.'
        29. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'If three men meet, of whom the first fully preserves interior peace, and the second gives thanks to God in illness, and the third serves with a pure mind, these three are doing the same work.'
        30. He also said, 'It is written: "As the hart longs for flowing streams, so longs my soul for Thee, O God." (Ps. 42.1) For truly harts in the desert devour many reptiles and when their venom burns them, they try to come to the springs, to drink so as to assuage the venom's burning. It is the same for the monks: sitting in the desert they are burned by the venom of evil demons, and they long for Saturday and Sunday to come to be able to go to the springs of water, that is to say, the body and blood of the Lord, so as to be purified from the bitterness of the evil one.'
        31. Abba Joseph asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'How should one fast?' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'For my part, I think it better that one should eat every day, but only a little, so as not to be satisfied.' Abba Joseph said to him, 'When you were younger, did you not fast two days at a time, abba?' The old man said: 'Yes, even for three days and four and the whole week. The Fathers tried all this out as they were able and they found it preferable to eat every day, but just a small amount. They have left us this royal way, which is light.'
        32. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> that every time he prepared to go to the synaxis, he sat alone and examined his thoughts for about an hour and then he set off.
        33. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'An inheritance has been left me, what ought I to do?' The old man said to him, 'Go, come back in three days and I will tell you.' So he returned as it had been decided. Then the old man said, 'What shall I say to you, brother? If I tell you to give it to the church, they will make banquets with it; if I tell you to give it to your relations, you will not receive any profit from it; if I tell you to give it to the poor, you will not do it. Do as you like, it is none of my business.'
        34. Another brother questioned him in these words: 'What does, "See that none of you repays evil for evil" mean?' (1 Thess. 5.15) The old man said to him, 'Passions work in four stages - first, in the heart; secondly, in the face; thirdly, in words; and fourthly, it is essential not to render evil for evil in deeds. If you can purify your heart, passion will not come into your expression; but if it comes into your face, take care not to speak; but if you do speak, cut the conversation short in case you render evil for evil.'
        35. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Vigilance, self-knowledge and discern- ment; these are the guides of the soul.'
        36. He also said, 'To throw yourself before God, not to measure your progress, to leave behind all self-will; these are the instruments for the work of the soul.'
        37. He also said, 'The victory over all the afflictions that befall you, is, to keep silence.'
        38. He also said, 'All bodily comfort is an abomination to the Lord.'
        39. He also said, 'Compunction has two sides: it is a good work and a good protection.'
        40. He also said, 'If a thought about bodily needs overtakes you, put the matter right at once; and if it comes a second time, put it right again, but the third time, if it presents itself, do not pay any attention to it, for it is not being any use to you.'
        41. He also said that a brother questioned Abba Adonias saying, 'What does it mean to become nothing?' The old man said, 'It means to place oneself beneath irrational beings and to know what they are without blame.'
        42. He also said, 'If man remembered that it is written: "By your words you will be justified and by your words you will be con- demned," (Matt. 12.37) he would choose to remain silent.'
        43. He also said, 'The beginning of evil is heedlessness.'
        44. He also said that Abba <persName ref="m13">Isidore</persName>, the priest of <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, spoke to the people one day saying, 'Brothers, is it not in order to endure affliction that we have come to this place? But now there is no affliction for us here. So I am getting my sheepskin ready to go where there is some affliction and there I shall find peace.'
        45. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'If I see something, do you want me to tell you about it?' The old man said to him, 'It is written: "If one gives answer before he hears, it is his folly and shame." (Prov.
        18.13) If you are questioned, speak; if not, remain silent.'
        46. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'Can a man put his trust in one single work?' The old man said to him that Abba John the Dwarf said, 'I would rather have a bit of all the virtues.'
        47. The old man said that a brother asked Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> if it is good to praise one's neighbour and that the old man said to him, 'It is better to be silent.'
        48. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Even if a man were to make a new heaven and earth, he could not live free of care.'
        49. He also said, 'As the breath which comes out of his nostrils, so does a man need humility and the fear of God.'
        50. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'What should I do?' The old man said to him, 'When Abraham entered the promised land he bought a sepulchre for himself and by means of this tomb, he inherited the land.' The brother said to him, 'What is the tomb?' The old man said, 'The place of tears and compunction.'
        51. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'If I give my brother a little bread or something else, the demons tarnish these gifts saying it was
        only done to please men.' The old man said to him, 'Even if it is to please men, we must give the brother what he needs.' He told him the following parable, 'Two farmers lived in the same town; one of them sowed and reaped a small and poor crop, while the other, who did not even trouble to sow reaped absolutely nothing. If a famine comes upon them, which of the two will find something to live on?' The brother replied, 'The one who reaped the small poor crop.' The old man said to him, 'So it is for us; we sow a little poor grain, so that we will not die of hunger.'
        52. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said that Abba Ammonas said, 'A man can spend his whole time carrying an axe without succeeding in cutting down the tree; while another, with experience of tree-felling brings the tree down with a few blows. He said that the axe is discernment.'
        53. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'How should a man behave?' The old man said to him, 'Look at <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName>: no-one found anything in him to complain about except for his prayers to the Lord his God.'
        54. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'The will of man is a brass wall between him and God and a stone of stumbling. When a man renounces it, he is also saying to himself, "By my God, I can leap over the wall." (Ps. 18.29) If a man's will is in line with what is right, then he can really labour.'
        55. He also said, 'As the old men were sitting at a meal one day, Abba Alonius got up to serve and when they saw that, they praised him. But he answered absolutely nothing. So one of them said to him privately, "Why don't you answer the old men who are compli- menting you?" Abba Alonius said to him, "If I were to reply to them I should be accepting their praises." '
        56. He also said, 'Men speak to perfection but they do precious little about it.'
        57. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Just a smoke drives the bees away and also takes the sweetness out of their work, so bodily ease drives the fear of God from the soul and dissipates all its activity.'
        58. A brother came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> in the second week of Lent and told him about his thoughts; he obtained peace, and said
        to him, 'I nearly did not come here today.' The old man asked him why. The brother said, 'I said to myself, "Perhaps he will not let me in because it is Lent." ' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'We have not been taught to close the wooden door but the door of our tongues.'
        59. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'You must flee from sensual things. In- deed, every time a man comes near to a struggle with sensuality, he is like a man standing on the edge of a very deep lake and the enemy easily throws him in whenever he likes. But if he lives far away from sensual things, he is like a man standing at a distance from the lake, so that even if the enemy draws him in order to throw him to the bottom, God sends him help at the very moment he is drawing him away and doing him violence.'
        60. He also said, 'Poverty, hardship, austerity and fasting, such are the instruments of the solitary life. It is written, "When these three men are together, Noah, Job, and <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName>, there am I, says the Lord." (of. Ezek. 14.14) Noah represents poverty, Job suffering and <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName> discernment. So, if these three works are found in a man, the Lord dwells in him.'
        61. Abba Joseph said, 'While we were sitting with Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> he mentioned <persName ref="m31">Agathon</persName> as "abba", and we said to him, "He is very young, why do you call him 'abba?' " Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, "Because his speech makes him worthy to be called abba." '
        62. A brother came to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> one day and said to him, 'What should I do, Father, for I am tempted to fornication? I went to Abba Ibiston and he said to me, "You must not let it stay with you."' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'Abba Ibiston's deeds are in heaven with the angels and he does not realise that you and I remain in fornication. If a monk controls his belly and his tongue and if he lives like an exile, be confident, he will not die.'
        63. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Teach your mouth to say that which you have in your heart.'
        64. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'If I see my brother committing a sin, is it right to conceal it?' The old man said to him, 'At the very moment when we hide our brother's fault, God hides our own and at the moment when we reveal our brother's fault, God reveals ours too.
        65. He said that someone asked Abba Paesius, 'What should I do about my soul, because it is insensitive and does not fear God?' He said to him, 'Go, and join a man who fears God, and live near him; he will teach you, too, to fear God.'
        66. He also said, 'If a monk can overcome two things, he can become free from the world.' The brother asked him what these two things were and he said, 'Bodily ease and vain-glory.'
        67. Abraham, the disciple of Abba <persName ref="m31">Agathon</persName>, questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'How do the demons fight against me?' Abba Poe- men said to him, 'The demons fight against you? They do not fight against us at all as long as we are doing our own will. For our own wills become the demons, and it is these which attack us in order that we may fulfil them. But if you want to see who the demons really fight against, it is against Moses and those who are like him.'
        68. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'God has given this way of life to Israel: to abstain from everything which is contrary to nature, that is to say, anger, fits of passion, jealousy, hatred and slandering the breth- ren; in short, everything that is characteristic of the old man.'
        69. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'Give me a word.' And he said to him, 'The Fathers put compunction as the beginning of every action.' The brother said again, 'Give me an- other word.' The old man replied, 'As far as you can, do some manual work so as to be able to give alms, for it is written that alms and faith purify from sin.' The brother said, 'What is faith?' The old man said, 'Faith is to live humbly and to give alms.'
        70. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'If I see a brother whom I have heard is a sinner, I do not want to take him into my cell, but when I see a good brother I am happy to be with him.' The old man said, 'If you do a little good to the good brother, do twice as much for the other. For he is sick. Now, there was an anchorite called Timothy in a coenobium. The abbot, having heard of a brother who was being tempted, asked Timothy about him, and the anchorite advised him to drive the brother away. Then when he had been driven away, the brother's temptation fell upon Timothy to the point where he was in danger. Then Timothy stood up before God and said, "I have sinned. Forgive me." Then a voice came which said to him, "Timothy, the only reason I have done this to you is because you despised your brother in the time of his tempta- tion." '
        71. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'The reason why we are so greatly tempted is because we do not guard our name and status, as Scrip- ture says. Do we not see that the Saviour gave peace to the Ca- naanite woman, accepting her as she was? (cf. Matt. 15) And the same for Abigail, because she said to David, "Upon me alone be the guilt," (1 Sam. 25.24) the Lord heard her and loved her. Abigail stands for the soul and David for God. So when the soul accuses herself before the Lord, the Lord loves her.'
        72. One day Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> went with Abba Anoub to the dis- trict of Diolcos. Arriving at the cemetery, they saw a woman in great sorrow, weeping bitterly. Standing there they watched her. Going a little further they met someone and Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> asked him, 'What is this woman weeping so bitterly for?' He said, 'Because her husband is dead and her son and her brother.' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to the brother, 'I tell you, if a man does not mortify all his carnal desires and acquire compunction like this, he cannot become a monk. Truly the whole of this woman's life and soul are turned to compunction.'
        73. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Do not judge yourself, but live with someone who knows how to behave himself properly.'
        74. He said that when a brother went to see Abba John the Dwarf, he offered him that charity of which the apostle speaks, 'Charity suffers long and is kind.' (1. Cor. 13.4)
        75. He said of Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> that Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> used to say of him, 'Through fearing God, he caused the spirit of God to dwell in him.'
        76. One of the Fathers related this about Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and his brethren: 'When they were living in <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName>, their mother wanted to see them and was not able to do so. So she took note of the time when they went to church and went to meet them. But when they saw her, they made a detour and closed the door in her face. But she beat on the door and cried with tears and groans, saying, "I must see you, my beloved children!" Hearing her, Abba Anoub went to
        Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and said to him, "What shall we do with this old woman who is weeping against the door?" From inside where he was standing, he heard her weeping with many groans and he said to her, "Woman, why are you crying out like this?" When she heard his voice, she cried out even more, weeping and saying, "I want to see you, my children. What will happen if I do see you? Am I not your mother? Was it not I who suckled you? So I was troubled when I heard your voice." The old man said to her, "Would you rather see us here or in the age which is to come?" She said to him, "If I do not see you here, shall I see you in the age to come?" He said to her, "If you refrain from seeing us now, you will see us yonder." So she departed full of joy and said, "If I shall see you perfectly yonder, I do not want to see you here."'
        77. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'High things, what are they?' The old man said to him, 'Righteousness.'
        78. Some heretics came to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> one day and began to speak evil of the archbishop of Alexandria suggesting that he had received the laying on of hands from priests. The old man, who had remained silent till then, called his brother and said, 'Set the table, give them something to eat and send them away in peace.'
        79. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said that a brother who lived with some other brothers asked Abba <persName ref="m2">Bessarion</persName>, 'What ought I to do?' The old man said to him, 'Keep silence and do not always be comparing yourself with others.'
        80. He also said, 'Do not give your heart to that which does not satisfy your heart.'
        81. He also said, 'If you take little account of yourself, you will have peace, wherever you live.'
        82. He also said that Abba Sisoes said, 'There is a kind of shame that contains a culpable lack of fear.'
        83. He also said, 'When self-will and ease become habitual, they overthrow a man.'
        84. He also said, 'If you are silent, you will have peace wherever you live.'
        85. He also said concerning Abba Pior that every day he made a new beginning.
        86. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'If a brother is involved in a sin and is converted, will God forgive him?' The old man said to him, 'Will not God, who has commanded men to act thus, do as much himself and even more? For God commanded Peter to forgive till seventy times seven.' (Matt. 18.22)
        87. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, saying, 'Is it good to pray?' The old man said that Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> said, This word comes from the mouth of the Lord, who said, "Comfort, comfort my people." ' (Is. 40.1)
        88. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Can a man keep all his thoughts in control, and not surrender one to the enemy?' And the old man said to him, 'There are some who receive ten and give one.'
        89. The same brother put the same question to Abba Sisoes who said to him, 'It is true that there are some who give nothing to the enemy.'
        90. There was a great hesychast in the mountain of Athlibeos. Some thieves fell upon him and the old man began to cry out. When they heard this the neighbours seized the robbers and took them to the magistrate who threw them into prison. The brothers were very sorry about this and they said, 'It is through us that they have been put in prison.' They got up and went to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> to tell him about it. He wrote to the old man saying, 'Consider the first betrayal and where it comes from and then examine the second. In truth, if you had not first failed within, you would not have committed the second betrayal.' On hearing Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s letter read (for he was renowned in all the district for not coming out of his cell), he arose, went to the city, got the robbers out of prison and liberated them in public.
        91. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'A monk does not complain of his lot, a monk does not return evil for evil, a monk is not angry.'
        92. Some old men came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and said to him, 'When we see brothers who are dozing at the synaxis, shall we rouse them so that they will be watchful?' He said to them, 'For my part
        when I see a brother who is dozing, I put his head on my knees and
        let him rest.'
        93. It was said of a brother that he had to fight against blasphemy and he was ashamed to admit it. He went where he heard some great old men lived to see them, in order to open his heart to them but when he got there, he was ashamed to admit his temptation. So he kept going to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>. The old man saw he was worried, and he was sorry he did not tell him what was wrong. So one day he forestalled him and said, 'For a long time you have been coming here to tell me what is troubling you, and when you are here you will not tell me about it, but each time you go away unhappy, keeping your thoughts to yourself. Now tell me, my child, what it is all about.' He said to him, 'The demon wars against me to make me blaspheme God and I am ashamed to say so.' So he told him all about it and immediately he was relieved. The old man said to him, 'Do not be unhappy, my child, but every time this thought comes to you say, "It is no affair of mine, may your blasphemy remain upon you, Satan, for my soul does not want it." Now everything that the soul does not desire, does not long remain,' and the brother went away healed.
        94. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'I see that wherever I go I find support.' The old man said to him, 'Even those who hold a sword in their hands have God who takes pity on them in the present time. If we are courageous, he will have mercy on us.'
        95. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'If a man accuses himself, he is protected on all sides.'
        96. He said that Abba Ammonas said, 'A man may remain for a hundred years in his cell without learning how to live in the cell.'
        97. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'If a man has attained to that which the Apostle speaks of "to the pure, everything is pure," (Titus 1.15) he sees himself less than all creatures.' The brother said, 'How can I deem myself less then a murderer?' The old man said, 'When a man has really comprehended this saying, if he sees a man committing a murder he says, "He has only committed this one sin but I commit sins every day."'
        98. A brother put the same question to Abba Anoub, telling him what Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> had said. Abba Anoub said to him, 'If a man really affirms this saying, when he sees his brother's faults he sees that his integrity exceeds his faults.' The brother said, 'What is integrity?' The old man replied, 'Always to accuse himself.'
        99. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'If I fall into a shameful sin, my conscience devours and accuses me saying: "Why have you fallen?" ' The old man said to him, 'At the moment when a man goes astray, if he says, I have sinned, immediately the sin ceases.'
        100. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'Why do the demons persuade my soul to look up to him who is superior to me and make me despise him who is my inferior?' The old man replied, 'About that, the Apostle has this to say: "In a great house there are not only vessels of gold and silver, but also of wood and earthenware; and if anyone purifies himself from what is ignoble, then he will be a vessel for noble use, consecrated and useful to the master of the house, ready for any good work."' (2 Tim. 2.20-21)
        101. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Why should I not be free to do without manifesting my thoughts to the old men?' The old man replied, 'Abba John the Dwarf said, "The enemy rejoices over nothing so much as over those who do not manifest their thoughts."'
        102. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'My heart becomes luke- warm when a little suffering comes my way.' The old man said to him, 'Do we not admire Joseph, a young man of seventeen, for enduring his temptation to the end? And God glorified him. Do we not also see Job, how he suffered to the end, and lived in endurance? Temptations cannot destroy hope in God.'
        103. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Life in the monastery demands three things: the first is humility, the next is obedience, and the third which sets them in motion and is like a goad is the work of the monastery.'
        104. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'In the time of my affliction I looked for something from one of the old men which would be useful to me and he gave it me as a free gift. Now if God comes to my aid, ought I in my turn to give it to others as a free gift, or
        rather give it back to him who gave it to me?' The old man said to him, 'What is right in the sight of God, is for you to give it back to him, for it is his.' The brother said, 'If I return it to him and he does not want it, but says to me, "Go, give it away however you like as a free gift," what shall I do?' The old man said to him, 'This thing belongs to him, but if it is offered to you spontaneously without your asking for it, it belongs to you. Whether he is a monk or a secular person, if he no longer wants what you ask for and gives it you, then it is right for you, with his knowledge, to give it away in his name as a free gift.'
        105. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> that he never wished to speak after another old man, but that he preferred to praise him in every- thing he had said.
        106. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Many of our Fathers have become very courageous in asceticism, but in fineness of perception there are very few.'
        107. One day Abba Isaac was sitting beside Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> when they heard a cock crow. Abba Isaac said to him, 'Is it possible to hear that here, abba?' He replied, 'Isaac, why do you make me talk? You and those like you hear those noises, but the vigilant man does not trouble about them.'
        108. It was said that if one of the brethren came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> the latter used to send him first to Abba Anoub, because he was older than he. But Abba Anoub would say to them, 'Go to my brother <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> because it is he who has the gift of speaking.' Whenever Abba Anoub came to sit beside Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> the latter refused to speak in his presence.
        109. A secular man of devout life came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>. Now it happened that there were other brethren with the old man, asking to hear a word from him. The old man said to the faithful secular, 'Say a word to the brothers.' When he insisted, the secular said, 'Please excuse me, abba; I myself have come to learn.' But he was urged on by the old man and so he said, 'I am a secular, I sell vegetables and do business; I take bundles to pieces, and make smaller ones; I buy cheap and sell dear. What is more I do not know how to speak of the Scriptures; so I will tell you a parable. A man
        said to his friends, "I want to go to see the emperor; come with me." One friend said to him, "I will go with you half the way." Then he said to another friend, "Come and go with me to the emperor," and he said to him, "I will take you as far as the emperor's palace." He said to a third friend, "Come with me to the emperor." He said, "I will come and take you to the palace and I will stay and speak and help you to have access to the emperor." ' They asked what was the point of the parable. He answered them, 'The first friend is asceti- cism, which leads the way; the second is chastity which takes us to heaven; and the third is almsgiving which with confidence presents us to God our King.' The brethren withdrew edified.
        110. A brother settled outside his village and did not return there for many years. He said to the brethren, 'See how many years it is since I went back to the village, while you often go up there.' This was told to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and the old man said, 'I used to go back up there at night and walk all round my village, so that the thought of not having gone up there would not cause me vain-glory.'
        111. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Give me a word,' and he said to him, 'As long as the pot is on the fire, no fly nor any other animal can get near it, but as soon as it is cold, these creatures get inside. So it is for the monk; as long as he lives in spiritual activities, the enemy cannot find a means of overthrowing him.'
        112. Abba Joseph said of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> that he said, 'This saying which is written in the Gospel: "Let him who has no sword, sell his mantle and buy one," (Luke 22.36) means this: let him who is at ease give it up and take the narrow way.'
        113. Some Fathers questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'If we see a brother in the act of committing a sin, do you think that we ought to reprove him?' The old man said to them, 'For my part, if I have to go out and I see someone committing a sin, I pass on my way without reproving him.'
        114. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'It is written: "Give witness of that which your eyes have seen" (cf. Proverbs 25.8); but I say to you even if you have touched with your hands, do not give witness. In truth, a brother was deceived in this respect; he thought he saw his brother in the act of sinning with a woman; greatly incensed, he
        drew near and kicked them (for he thought it was they), saying, "Now stop; how much longer will you go on?" Now it turned out that it was some sheaves of corn. That is the reason why I said to you: even if you touch with your hands, do not reprove.'
        115. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'What shall I do, for forni- cation and anger war against me?' The old man said, 'In this connec- tion David said: "I will pierce the lion and I will slay the bear" (cf
        1 Sam. 1735); that is to say: I will cut off anger and I will crush fornication with hard labour.'
        116. He also said, ' "Greater love hath no man than this that a man lay down his life for his friends." (John 15.13) In truth if someone hears an evil saying, that is, one which harms him, and in his turn, he wants to repeat it, he must fight in order not to say it. Or if someone is taken advantage of and he bears it, without retalia- ting at all, then he is giving his life for his neighbour.'
        117. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'What is a hypocrite?' The old man said to him, 'A hypocrite is he who teaches his neighbour something he makes no effort to do himself. It is written, "Why do you see the speck that is in your brother's eye, but do not notice the log that is in your own eye, etc."' (Matt. 7.3-4)
        118. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'What does it mean to be angry with your brother without a cause?' He said, 'If your brother hurts you by his arrogance and you are angry with him because of it, that is getting angry without cause. If he plucks out your right eye and cuts off your right hand, and you get angry with him, you are angry without cause. But if he separates you from God, then be angry with him.'
        119. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> what he should do about his sins. The old man said to him, 'He who wishes to purify his faults purifies them with tears and he who wishes to acquire virtues, acquires them with tears; for weeping is the way the Scriptures and our Fathers give us, when they say "Weep!" Truly, there is no other way than this.'
        120. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'What does it mean to repent of a fault?' The old man said, 'Not to commit it again in future. This is the reason the righteous were called blameless, for they gave up their faults and became righteous.'
        121. He also said, 'The wickedness of men is hidden behind their backs.'
        122. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'What ought I to do about all the turmoils that trouble me?' The old man said to him, 'In all our afflictions let us weep in the presence of the goodness of God, until he shows mercy on us.'
        123. The brother asked him, 'What ought I to do about the sterile affections that I have?' He said to him, 'There are men who tire themselves to death involving themselves in the friendships of this world. But keep yourself away from all that and do not get involved in such relationships and they will be transformed of their own accord.'
        124. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Can a man be dead?' He replied, 'He who is inclined to sin starts to die, but he who applies himself to good will live and will put it into practice.'
        125. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said that blessed Abba <persName ref="m1">Anthony</persName> used to say, 'The greatest thing a man can do is to throw his faults before the Lord and to expect temptation to his last breath.'
        126. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> was asked for whom this saying is suitable, 'Do not be anxious about tomorrow.' (Matt. 6.34) The old man said, 'It is said for the man who is tempted and has not much strength, so that he should not be worried, saying to himself, "How long must I suffer this temptation?" He should rather say every day to himself, "Today."'
        127. He also said, 'Instructing one's neighbour is for the man who is whole and without passions; for what is the use of building the house of another, while destroying one's own?'
        128. He also said, 'What is the good of giving oneself to a trade without seeking to learn it?'
        129. He also said, 'Everything that goes to excess comes from the demons.'
        130. He also said, 'When a man prepares to build a house, he gathers together all he needs to be able to construct it, and he collects different sorts of materials. So it is with us; let us acquire a little of the virtues.'
        131. Some Fathers asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'How could Abba Nis- terus bear so well with his discipline?' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to them, 'If I had been in his place, I would even have put a pillow under his head.' Abba Anoub said, 'And what would you have said to God?' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'I would have said to him: "You have said, 'First take the log out of your own eye, then you will see clearly to take the speck out of your brothers' eye." ' (Matt. 7.5)
        132. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Because of our need to eat and to sleep, we do not see the simple things.'
        133. He also said, 'Many become powerful, but few eminent.'
        134. He also said, groaning, 'All the virtues come to this house except one and without that virtue it is hard for a man to stand.' Then they asked him what virtue was, and he said, 'For a man to blame himself.'
        135. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> often said, 'We do not need anything except a vigilant spirit.'
        136. One of the Fathers asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Who is he who says, "I am a companion of all who fear Thee," ' (Ps. 119.63) and the old man said, 'It is the Holy Spirit who says that.'
        137. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said that a brother asked Abba Simon, 'If I come out of my cell and find my brother amusing himself, I amuse myself with him and if I find him in the act of laughing, I laugh with him. Then when I return to my cell, I am no longer at peace.' The old man said to him, 'So, when you come out of your cell and find people laughing or talking you want to laugh and talk with them, and when you return to your cell, you expect to find yourself as you were before?' The brother said, 'What should I do?' The old man replied, 'Be watchful inwardly; be watchful outwardly.'
        138. Abba <persName ref="m4">Daniel</persName> said, 'We went one day to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and ate together. After we had eaten he said to us, "Go, rest a little, brothers." The brothers went to take a little rest but I wanted to speak to him privately to I went to his cell. When he saw me coming he settled himself as though he were asleep. For that was always the old man's way, to do everything in secret so that no one noticed it.'
        139. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'If you have visions or hear voices do not
        tell your neighbour about it, for it is a delusion in the battle.'
        140. He also said, 'The first time flee; the second time, flee; and the third, become like a sword.'
        141. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to Abba Isaac, 'Let go of a small part of your righteousness and in a few days you will be at peace.'
        142. A brother came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and while several of them were sitting round, he praised a brother for hating evil. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to the one who had spoken, 'What does it mean to hate evil?' The brother was surprised and found nothing to say in reply. Getting up, he made a prostration before the old man, and said, 'Tell me what hatred of evil is?' The old man said to him, 'Hatred of evil is to hate one's thoughts and to praise one's neighbour.'
        143. A brother went to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and said to him, 'What ought I to do?' The old man said to him, 'Go and join one who says "What do I want?" and you will have peace.'
        144. Abba Joseph related that Abba Isaac said, 'I was sitting with Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> one day and I saw him in ecstasy and I was on terms of great freedom of speech with him, I prostrated myself before him and begged him, saying, "Tell me where you were." He was forced to answer and he said, "My thought was with Saint Mary, the Mother of God, as she wept by the cross of the Saviour. I wish I could always weep like that." '
        145. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'What can I do about this weight which is crushing me?' The old man said to him, 'In ships, small or large, there are tow-ropes which are lashed round the centre when the wind is unfavourable, to draw the small craft slowly along until God sends the wind. When the sailors notice that darkness is falling, then they throw out anchors so that the vessels may not drift away.'
        146. A brother asked Abba Poeman about the harm which he was suffering through his thoughts. The old man said to him, 'In this matter it is like a man who has fire on his left and a cup of water on his right. If the fire kindles, he must take water from the cup and extinguish it. The fire is the enemy's seed, and the water is the act of throwing oneself before God.'
        147. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Is it better to speak or to be silent?' The old man said to him, 'The man who speaks for God's sake does well; but he who is silent for God's sake also does well.'
        148. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'How can a man avoid speaking ill of his neighbour?' The old man said to him, 'We and our brothers are two images; when a man is watchful about himself, and has to reproach himself, in his heart he thinks his brother better than he; but when he appears to himself to be good, then he thinks his brother evil compared to himself.'
        149. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> about accidie. The old man said to him, 'Accidie is there every time one begins something, and there is no worse passion, but if a man recognizes it for what it is, he will gain peace.'
        150. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'In Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> we see three bodily activities; abstinence from food until the evening every day, silence, and much manual work.'
        151. He said that Abba Theonas said, 'Even if a man acquires a virtue, God does not grant him grace for himself alone.' He knew that he was not faithful in his own labour, but that if he went to his companion, God would be with him.
        152. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'I want to go to the monas- tery, and dwell there.' The old man said to him, 'If you want to go the the monastery, you must be careful about every encounter and everything you do, or you will not be able to do the work of the monastery; for you will not have the right even to drink a single cup there.'
        153. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'What ought I to do?' He said, 'It is written, "I confess my iniquity, I am sorry for my sin."'(Ps. 38.18)
        154. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Fornication and slander, are two thoughts that should never be talked about or pondered in the heart; for if you want to understand them in the heart, it does no good: but if you fight shy of them, you will obtain peace.'
        155. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>'s brethren said to him, 'Let us leave this place, for the monasteries here worry us and we are losing our souls; even
        the little children who cry do not let us have interior peace.' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to them, 'Is it because of voices of angels that you wish to go away from here?'
        156. Abba Bitimius asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'If someone has a griev- ance against me, and I ask his pardon but cannot convince him, what is to be done?' The old man said to him, 'Take two other brothers with you and ask his pardon. If he is not satisfied, take five others. If he is still not satisfied by them, take a priest. If even so he is not satisfied, then pray to God without anxiety, that he may himself satisfy him and do not worry about it.'
        157. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'To instruct your neighbour is the same thing as reproving him.'
        158. He also said, 'Do not do your own will; you need rather to humble yourself before your brother.'
        159. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> saying, 'I have found a place where peace is not disturbed by the brethren; do you advise me to live there?' The old man said to him, 'The place for you is where you will not harm your brother.'
        160. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'These three things are the most helpful of all: fear of the Lord; prayer; and doing good to one's neighbour.'
        161. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'My body is getting sick, and yet my passions are not getting weaker.' The old man said to him, 'The passions are like thorns.'
        162. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'What ought I to do?' The old man said to him, 'When God is watching over us, what have we got to worry about?' The brother said to him, 'Our sins.' Then the old man said, 'Let us enter into our cell, and sitting there, remember our sins, and the Lord will come and help us in everything.'
        163. A brother going to market asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'How do you advise me to behave?' The old man said to him, 'Make friends with anyone who tries to bully you and sell your produce in peace.'
        164. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Teach your mouth to say what is in your heart.'
        165. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> was asked about impurities and he replied, 'If we are active and very watchful, we shall not find impurities in ourselves.'
        166. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Since Abba <persName ref="m30">Moses</persName> and the third genera- tion in <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, the brothers do not make progress any more.'
        167. He also said, 'A man who stays in his place in life will not be troubled.'
        168. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, "How should I live in the cell?' He said to him, 'Living in your cell clearly means manual work, eating only once a day, silence, meditation; but really making progress in the cell, means to experience contempt for yourself wherever you go, not to neglect the hours of prayer and to pray secretly. If you happen to have time without manual work, take up prayer and do it without disquiet. The perfection of these things is to live in good company and be free from bad.'
        169. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'If a brother has a little money which belongs to me, do you advise me to ask him for it?' The old man said to him, 'Ask him for it once.' The brother said to him, 'And then what should I do? For I cannot control my thoughts.' The old man said to him, 'Be quiet and do not think about it. But do not distress your brother.'
        170. It happened that several Fathers went to the home of a friend of Christ; among them was Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>. During the meal, meat was served and everyone ate some except Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>. The old men knew his discretion and they were surprised that he did not eat it. When they got up, they said to him, 'You are <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, and yet you behaved like this?' The old man answered, 'Forgive me, my Fathers; you have eaten and no-one is shocked; but if I had eaten, since many brothers come to me, they would have suffered harm, for they would have said <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> has eaten meat; why should not we eat it ourselves?' So they admired his discernment.
        171. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'I say this about myself: I am thrown into the place where Satan is thrown.'
        172. He also said to Abba Anoub, 'Turn away your eyes lest they behold vanity; (cf. Ps. 11937) for licence causes souls to perish.'
        173. One day when Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> was sitting down, Paesius fought with his brother till the blood ran from their heads. The old man said absolutely nothing to them. Then Abba Anoub came in and saw them, he said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Why have you let the brothers fight without saying anything to them?' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> replied, They are brothers, and they will make it up again.' Abba Anoub said, 'What do you mean? You saw them behaving like this, and all you say is they will make it up again?' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, Try and think that inwardly I was not here to see it.'
        174. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Some brothers live with me; do you want me to be in charge of them?' The old man said to him, 'No, just work first and foremost, and if they want to live like you, they will see to it themselves.' The brother said to him, 'But it is they themselves, Father who want me to be in charge of them.' The old man said to him, 'No, be their example, not their legislator.'
        175. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said 'If a brother comes to visit you and you realise that you have not profited by his visit, search your heart, and discover what you were thinking about before he came, and then you will understand why his visit was useless. If you do this with humility and care, you will be blameless with regard to your neigh- bour, bearing your own weaknesses. If a man settles somewhere with care, he does not sin for he is in the presence of God. I see that this is how a man acquires the fear of God.'
        176. He also said, 'A man who lives with a boy, and is incited by him to no matter what passions of the old man, and yet keeps him with him, that man is like someone who has a field which is eaten up with maggots.'
        177. He also said, 'Wickedness does not do away with wicked- ness; but if someone does you wrong, do good to him, so that by your action you destroy his wickedness.'
        178. He also said, 'David, when he was fighting with the lion, seized it by the throat and killed it immediately. If we take ourselves by the throat and by the belly, with the help of God, we shall overcome the invisible lion.'
        179. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> this question, 'What shall I do, because trouble comes to me and I am overwhelmed by it?' The old man said, 'Violence makes both small and great to be over-
        thrown.'
        180. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> that he dwelt at <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> with his two brothers, and the younger one was a nuisance to them. So he said to the other brother, 'This lad is making us powerless, let us get up and go away from here.' So they went away and left him. When he saw that they did not come back for a long time, the young brother realized that they were going far away and he began to run after them, crying out. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Let us wait for our brother, for he is worn out.' When he reached them he bowed to them and said, 'Where are you going? Are you leaving me on my own?' The old man said to him, 'It is because you are a worry to us that we are going away.' He said to them, 'Yes, yes, let us go together wherever you wish.' The old man, seeing his lack of mal- ice, said to his brother, 'Brother, let us go back, for he is not doing this on purpose but it is the devil who is doing it.' So they turned back and went home again.
        181. The begumen of a monastery asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'How can I acquire the fear of God?' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'How can we acquire the fear of God when our belly is full of cheese and preserved foods?'
        182. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'Abba, there were two men, one a monk and the other a secular. One evening the monk decided to put off the habit the next morning and the secular decided to become a monk. Now both of them died in the night. How will they be judged?' The old man said to him, 'The monk died a monk, the secular died a secular; in fact they died in the state in which they found themselves.'
        183. Abba John, who had been exiled by the Emperor Marcian, said, 'We went to <placeName ref="p2">Syria<geo>37.5 37.5</geo></placeName> one day to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and we wanted to ask him about purity of heart. But the old man did not know Greek and no interpreter could be found. So, seeing our embarrass- ment, the old man began to speak Greek, saying, 'The nature of water is soft, that of stone is hard; but if a bottle is hung above the stone, allowing the water to fall drop by drop, it wears away the stone. So it is with the word of God; it is soft and our heart is hard,
        but the man who hears the word of God often, opens his heart to the fear of God.'
        184. Abba Isaac came to see Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and found him wash- ing his feet. As he enjoyed freedom of speech with him he said, 'How is it that others practice austerity and treat their bodies hardly?' Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said to him, 'We have not been taught to kill our bodies, but to kill our passions.'
        185. He also said, 'There are three things which I am not able to do without: food, clothing and sleep; but I can restrict them to some extent.'
        186. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'I eat a lot of vegetables.' The old man said, 'That does not help you; rather eat bread and a few vegetables, and do not go back to your relations for what you need.'
        187. It was said of Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> that if some old men were sitting with him, speaking of the ancients, and Abba Sisoes was mentioned, he would say, 'Keep silence about Abba Sisoes, for that which concerns him goes beyond what can be said.'
        188. He also said, 'Teach your heart to guard that which your tongue teaches.'
        189. A brother questioned Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, saying, 'I am losing my soul through living near my abba; should I go on living with him?' The old man knew that he was finding this harmful and he was surprised that he even asked if he should stay there. So he said to him, 'Stay if you want to.' The brother left him and stayed on there. He came back again and said, 'I am losing my soul.' But the old man did not tell him to leave. He came a third time and said, 'I really cannot stay there any longer.' Then Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'Now you are saving yourself; go away and do not stay with him any longer,' and he added, 'When someone sees that he is in danger of losing his soul, he does not need to ask advice. It is right to ask about secret thoughts and then it is up to the old man to test them; but with visible faults, do not ask; cut them off at once.'
        190. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said that Abba Paphnutius was great and he had recourse to short prayers.
        191. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'How should I behave in the place where I live?' The old man said, 'Have the mentality of an exile in the place where you live, do not desire to be listened to and you will have peace.'
        192. He also said, 'This voice cries out to a man to his last breath, "Be converted today."'
        193. He also said, 'David wrote to Joab, "Continue the battle and you will take the city and sack it." Now the city is the enemy.'
        194. He also said, 'Joab said to the people, "Be courageous and let us play the man for our people, and for the cities of our God." (I Chron. 1913) Now we ourselves are these men.'
        195. He also said, 'If Moses had not led his sheep to Midian he would not have seem him who was in the bush.' (cf. Exodus 3. 2-7)
        196. A brother came to Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> and asked, 'How did you come here?' and he told him, 'If I were to die in <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName> with my brothers, I would be willing, and here we are.'
        197. He also said, 'If a man understands something and does not practise it, how can he teach it to his neighbour?'
        198. He also said, 'A man who lives with a companion ought to be like a stone pillar; hurt him, and he does not get angry, praise him, and he is not puffed up.'
        199. He also said, 'A man knows nothing about the powers that are outside him; but if they enter into him, he must fight them and drive them out.'
        200. He also said, 'Not understanding what has happened pre- vents us from going on to something better.'
        201. He also said, 'Do not lay open your conscience to anyone whom you do not trust in your heart.'
        202. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'If I am in a place where there are enemies, I become a soldier.'
        203. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> heard of someone who had gone all week without eating and then had lost his temper. The old man said, 'He could do without food for six days, but he could not cast out anger.'
        204. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'I will tell you why we have so much difficulty; it is because we do not care about our brother whom Scripture tells us to receive. Moreover we do not remember the woman of Canaan (cf. Matt. 15.22) who followed the Lord crying and begging for her daughter to be cured, and the Lord heard her and gave her peace.'
        205. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said, 'If the soul keeps far away from all discourse in words, from all disorder and human disturbance, the Spirit of God will come in to her and she who was barren will be fruitful.'
        206. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'How should those who are in the monastery behave?' The old man said to him, 'Whoever lives in the monastery should see all the brethren as one; he should guard his eyes and his lips; and then he will be at peace without anxiety.'
        207. Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName> said this about the son of Shemai, 'His mis- take was to justify himself; whoever does that destroys himself.'
        208. A brother asked Abba <persName ref="m23">Poemen</persName>, 'What can I do about my sins?' and the old man said to him, 'Weep interiorly, for both deliver- ance from faults and the acquisition of virtues are gained through compunction.'
        209. He also said,' Weeping is the way that Scripture and our Fathers have handed on to us.'  
    </p>
</div>
<div type="section" n="Pambo">
    <p>
        1. There was a monk named <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> and they said of him that he spent three years saying to God, 'Do not glorify me on earth.' But God glorified him so that one could not gaze steadfastly at him
        because of the glory of his countenance.
        2. Two brethren came to see Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> one day and the first asked him, 'Abba, I fast for two days, then I eat two loaves; am I saving my soul, or am I going the wrong way?' The second said, 'Abba, every day I get two pence from my manual work, and I keep a little for my food and give the rest in alms; shall I be saved or shall I be lost?' They remained a long time questioning him and still the old man gave them no reply. After four days they had to leave and the priests comforted them saying, 'Do not be troubled, brothers. God gives the reward. It is the old man's custom not to speak readily till God inspires him.' So they went to see the old man and said to him, 'Abba, pray for us.' He said to them, 'Do you want to go away?' They said, 'Yes.' Then, giving his mind to their works and writing on the ground he said, 'If <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> fasted for two days together and ate two loaves, would he become a monk that way? No. And if <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> works to get two pence and gives them in alms, would he become a monk that way? No, not that way either.' He said to them, 'The works are good, but if you guard your conscience towards your neighbour, then you will be saved.' They were satisfied and went away joyfully.
        3. Four monks of <placeName>Scetis<geo>30.35 30.20</geo></placeName>, clothed in skins, came one day to see the great <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName>. Each one revealed the virtue of his neighbour. The first fasted a great deal; the second was poor; the third had acquired great charity; and they said of the fourth that he had lived for twenty-two years in obedience to an old man. Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> said to them, 'I tell you, the virtue of this last one is the greatest. Each of the others has obtained the virtue he wished to acquire; but the last one, restraining his own will, does the will of another. Now it is of such men that the martyrs are made, if they persevere to the end.'
        4. Athanasius, Archbishop of Alexandria, of holy memory, begged Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> to come down from the desert to Alexandria. He went down, and seeing an actress he began to weep. Those who were present asked him the reason for his tears, and he said, 'Two things make me weep: one, the loss of this woman; and the other, that I am not so concerned to please God as she is to please wicked men.'
        5. Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> said, 'By the grace of God, since I left the world,
        I have not said one word of which I repented afterwards.'
        6. He also said, 'The monk should wear a garment of such a kind that he could throw it out of his cell and no-one would steal it from him for three days.'
        7. Once it happened that Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> made the journey to <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13 </geo></placeName> with some brothers. Meeting some lay people who were sitting down, he said to them, 'Stand up, greet the monks, so that you may be blessed, for they speak with God without interruption and their lips are holy.'
        <listEvent>
            <event><desc>Pambo traveled to Egypt</desc></event> 
            <listRelation><relation type="traveled-to" name="traveler" active="m24" passive="p8">
                <desc>traveled to
                    <placeName ref="p8">Egypt<geo>30.2 31.13</geo></placeName>
                </desc></relation>
            </listRelation>
        </listEvent>
        8. They said of Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> that as he was dying, at the very hour of his death, he said to the holy men who were standing near him, 'Since I came to this place of the desert and built my cell and dwelt here, I do not remember having eaten bread which was not the fruit of my hands and I have not repented of a word I have said up to the present time; and yet I am going to God as one who has not yet begun to serve him.'
        9. He was greater than many others in that if he was asked to interpret part of the Scriptures or a spiritual saying, he would not reply immediately, but he would say he did not know that saying. If he was asked again, he would say no more.
        10. Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> said, 'If you have a heart, you can be saved.'
        11. The priest of Nitria asked him how the brethren ought to live. He replied, 'With much labour, guarding their consciences towards their neighbour.'
        12. They said of Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> that he was like Moses, who received the image of the glory of Adam when his face shone. His face shone like lightening and he was like a king sitting on his throne. It was the same with Abba Silvanus and Abba Sisoes.
        13. They said of Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> that his face never smiled. So one day, wishing to make him laugh, the demons stuck wing feathers on to a lump of wood and brought it in making an uproar and saying, 'Go, go.' When he saw them Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> began to laugh and the demons started to say in chorus, 'Ha! ha! <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName> has laughed!' But in reply he said to them, 'I have not laughed, but I made fun of your powerlessness, because it takes so many of you
        to carry a wing.'
        14. Abba <persName ref="m8">Theodore of Pherme</persName> asked Abba <persName ref="m24">Pambo</persName>, 'Give me a word.' With much difficulty he said to him, 'Theodore, go and have pity on all, for through pity, one finds freedom of speech before God.'
    </p>
</div> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
