<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://syriaca.org/documentation/syriaca-tei-main.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Sayings of the Desert Fathers, an imagined network</title>
                <editor ref="https://github.com/alexvawter">Alexandria Vawter</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>ISAW, Fall 2017</p>
                <p>Introduction to Digital Humanities</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Apophthegmata Patrum, The Alphabetical Collection</p>
                <p>translated by Benedicta Ward</p>
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
     
            <div type= "section" n="alpha">
                <p n="1"> 1. When the holy Abba <persName xml:id="m1">Anthony</persName> lived in the desert he was beset by accidie, and attacked by many sinful thoughts. He said to God, <q who="#m1">'Lord,  I want to be saved but these thoughts do not leave me alone; what shall I do in my affliction? How can I be saved?'</q> A short while afterwards, when he got up to go out, <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> saw a man like himself sitting at his work, getting up from his work to pray, then sitting down and plaiting a rope, then getting up again to pray. It was an angel of the Lord sent to correct and reassure him. He heard the angel saying to him, 'Do this and you will be saved.' At these words, <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> was filled with joy and courage. He did this, and he was saved.</p>
                <p n="2"> 2. When the same Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> thought about the depth of the judgements of God, he asked,<q who="#m1">'Lord, how is it that some die when they are young, while others drag on to extreme old age? Why are there those who are poor and those who are rich? Why do wicked men prosper and why are the just in need?'</q> He heard a voice answering him, '<persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>, keep your attention on yourself; these things are according to the judgement of God, and it is not to your advantage to know anything about them.'</p> 
                <p n="3"> 3. Someone asked Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> , 'What must one do in order to please God?' The old man replied, <q who="#m1">'Pay attention to what I tell you: whoever you may be, always have God before your eyes; whatever you do, do it according to the testimony of the holy Scriptures; in whatever place you live, do not easily leave it. Keep these three precepts and you will be saved.'</q></p>
                <p n="4"> 4. Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> said to Abba <persName xml:id="m2">Poemen </persName>, <q type="conversation" who="#m1">'This is the great work of a man: always to take the blame for his own sins before God and to expect temptation to his last breath.'</q> 
                        <listPerson>
                            <person><persName ref="#m1"></persName></person>
                            <listRelation><relation type="conversation" name="monk" active="#m1" passive="#m2"/></listRelation>
                        </listPerson>
                        </p>
                <p n="5">5. He also said, 'Whoever has not experienced temptation cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.' He even added, 'Without temp- tations no-one can be saved.'</p>
                <p n="6"> 6. Abba Pambo asked Abba <persName ref="#m1" ><persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName></persName>, 'What ought I to do?' and the old man said to him, 'Do not trust in your own righteousness, do not worry about the past, but control your tongue and your stomach.'</p> 
                <p n="7"> 7. Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'I saw the snares that the enemy spreads out over the world and I said groaning, "What can get through from such snares?" Then I heard a voice saying to me, "Humility." ' </p>
                <p n="8">8. He also said, 'Some have afflicted their bodies by asceticism,
            but they lack discernment, and so they are far from God.'</p>
                <p n="9">9. He also said, 'Our life and our death is with our neighbour. If we gain our brother, we have gained God, but if we scandalise our brother, we have sinned against Christ.'</p>
                <p n="10">10 . He said also, 'Just as fish die if they stay too long out of water, so the monks who loiter outside their cells or pass their time with men of the world lose the intensity of inner peace. So like a fish going towards the sea, we must hurry to reach our cell, for fear that if we delay outside we will lose our interior watchfulness.'</p>
               <p n="11">11. He said also, 'He who wishes to live in solitude in the desert is delivered from three conflicts: hearing, speech, and sight; there is only one conflict for him and that is with fornication.'</p>
                <p n="12">12.<persName xml:id="g1">Some brothers</persName> came to find Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> to tell him about the visions they were having, and to find out from him if they were true or if they came from the demons. They had a donkey which died on the way. When they reached the place where the old man was, he said to them before they could ask him anything, 'How was it that the little donkey died on the way here?' They said, 'How do you know about that, Father?' And he told them, 'The demons shewed me what happened.' So they said, 'That was what we came to question you about, for fear we were being deceived, for we have visions which often turn out to be true.' Thus the old man convinced them, by the example of the donkey, that their visions came from the demons.
                     </p>
              <p n="13">13. A <persName xml:id="a1">hunter</persName> in the desert saw Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> enjoying himself with the brethren and he was shocked. Wanting to show him that it was necessary sometimes to meet the needs of the brethren, the old man said to him,<q who="#m1">'Put an arrow in your bow and shoot it.'</q> So he did. The old man then said, 'Shoot another,' and he did so. Then the old man said,<q who="#m1">'Shoot yet again,'</q> and the hunter replied <q who="#a1">'If I bend my bow so much I will break it.'</q> Then the old man said to him, <q who="#m1">'It is the same with the work of God. If we stretch the brethren beyond measure they will soon break. Sometimes it is necessary to come down to meet their needs.'</q> When he heard these words the hunter was pierced by compunction and, greatly edified by the old man, he went away. As for the brethren, they went home strengthened.</p>
              <p n="14"> 14. Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> heard of a very young monk who had performed a miracle on the road. Seeing the old men walking with difficulty along the road, he ordered the wild asses to come and carry them until they reached Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName>. Those whom they had carried told Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> about it. He said to them, 'This monk seems to me to be a ship loaded with goods but I do not know if he will reach harbour.' After a while, <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> suddenly began to weep, to tear his hair and lament. His disciples said to him, 'Why are you weeping, Father?' and the old man replied, 'A great pillar of the Church has just fallen (he meant the young monk) but go to him and see what has happened.' So the disciples went and found the monk sitting on a mat and weeping for the sin he had committed. Seeing the disciples of the old man he said, 'Tell the old man to pray that God will give me just ten days and I hope I will have made satisfaction.' But in the space of five days he died.</p>
            <p n="15">   15. The brothers praised a monk before Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>. When the monk came to see him, <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> wanted to know how he would bear insults; and seeing that he could not bear them at all, he said to him, 'You are like a village magnificently decorated on the outside, but destroyed from within by robbers.'</p>
            <p n="16">  16. A brother said to Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>, 'Pray for me.' The old man said to him, 'I will have no mercy upon you, nor will God have any, if you yourself do not make an effort and if you do not pray to God.' '</p>
            <p n="17">  17. One day <name xml:id="g2">some old men</name> came to see Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>. In the midst of them was Abba <persName xml:id="m3">Joseph</persName>. Wanting to test them, the old man suggested a text from the Scriptures, and, beginning with the youngest, he asked them what it meant. Each gave his opinion as he was able. But to each one the old man said,<q who="#m1">'You have not understood it.'</q> Last of all he said to Abba <persName ref="#m3">Joseph</persName>,<q who="#m1"> 'How would you explain this saying?'</q> and he replied, <q who="#m3">'I do not know.'</q> Then Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said,<q who="#m1">'Indeed, Abba <persName ref="#m3">Joseph</persName> has found the way, for he has said: "I do not know."'</q></p>
             <p n="18"> 18.<name xml:id="g3">Some brothers</name> were coming from Scetis to see Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName>. When they were getting into a boat to go there, they found an old man who also wanted to go there. The brothers did not know him. They sat in the boat, occupied by turns with the words of the Fathers, Scripture and their manual work. As for the old man, he remained silent. When they arrived on shore they found that the old man was going to the cell of Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> too. When they reached the place, <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said to them, 'You found this old man a good companion for the journey?' Then he said to the old man, 'You have brought many good brethren with you, father.' The old man said, 'No doubt they are good, but they do not have a door to their house and anyone who wishes can enter the stable and loose the ass.' He meant that the brethren said whatever came into their mouths.
                 <listEvent>
                     <event><desc>Some brothers from Scetis visted Anthony</desc></event> 
                     <listRelation>
                         <relation type="visit" name="vistor" active="#g3" passive="#m1">
                             <desc>
                                 <location>
                                 <placeName>Scetis<addName>Wadi El Natrun</addName></placeName>
                                 <geo>30.35 30.20</geo> 
                                 </location>
                             </desc></relation></listRelation></listEvent> 
                 </p>
     <p n="19">    19. The brethren came to the Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> and said to him, 'Speak a word; how are we to be saved?' The old man said to them, 'You have heard the Scriptures. That should teach you how.' But they said, 'We want to hear from you too, Father.' Then the old man said to them, 'The Gospel says, "if anyone strikes you on one cheek, turn to him the other also."' (Matt. 5.39) They said, 'We cannot do that.' The old man said, 'If you cannot offer the other cheek, at least allow one cheek to be struck.' 'We cannot do that either,' they said. So he said, 'If you are not able to do that, do not return evil for evil,' and they said, 'We cannot do that either.' Then the old man said to his disciple, 'Prepare a little brew of corn for these invalids. If you cannot do this, or that, what can I do for you? What you need is prayers.'</p>
 <p n="20">   20. A brother renounced the world and gave his goods to the poor, but he kept back a little for his personal expenses. He went to see Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>. When he told him this, the old man said to him, 'If you want to be a monk, go into the village, buy some meat, cover your naked body with it and come here like that.' The brother did so, and the dogs and birds tore at his flesh. When he came back the old man asked him whether he had followed his advice. He showed him his wounded body, and Saint <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'Those who renounce the world but want to keep something for themselves are torn in this way by the demons who make war on them.'</p>

 <p n="21">21. It happened one day that one of the brethren in the monas- tery of Abba Elias was tempted. Cast out of the monastery, he went over the mountain to Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>. The brother lived near him for a while and then <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> sent him back to the monastery from which he had been expelled. When the brothers saw him they cast him out yet again, and he went back to Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> saying, 'My Father, they will not receive me.' Then the old man sent them a message saying, 'A boat was shipwrecked at sea and lost its cargo; with great difficulty it reached the shore; but you want to throw into the sea that which has found a safe harbour on the shore.' When the brothers understood that it was Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> who had sent them this monk, they received him at once.</p>
        <p n="22">22. Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'I believe that the body possesses a natu- ral movement, to which it is adapted, but which it cannot follow without the consent of the soul; it only signifies in the body a movement without passion. There is another movement, which comes from the nourishment and warming of the body by eating and drinking, and this causes the heat of the blood to stir up the body to work. That is why the apostle said, "Do not get drunk with wine for that is debauchery." (Ephes. 5.18) And in the Gospel the Lord also recommends this to his disciples: "Take heed to your- selves lest your hearts be weighed down with dissipation and drunk- enness." (Luke 21:34) But there is yet another movement which afflicts those who fight, and that comes from the wiles and jealousy of the demons. You must understand what these three bodily move- ments are: one is natural, one comes from too much to eat, the third is caused by the demons.'</p>
          <p n="23">23. He also said, 'God does not allow the same warfare and temptations to this generation as he did formerly, for men are weaker now and cannot bear so much.'</p>
          <p n="24">24. It was revealed to Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> in his desert that there was one who was his equal in the city. He was a doctor by profession and whatever he had beyond his needs he gave to the poor, and every day he sang the Sanctus with the angels.</p>
         <p n="25">25. Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'A time is coming when men will go mad, and when they see someone who is not mad, they will attack him saying, "You are mad, you are not like us."'</p>
          <p n="26">26. The brethren came to Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> and laid before him a passage from Leviticus. The old man went out into the desert, secretly followed by Abba Ammonas, who knew that this was his custom. Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> went a long way off and stood there praying, crying in a loud voice, 'God, send Moses, to make me under- stand this saying.' Then there came a voice speaking with him. Abba Ammonas said that although he heard the voice speaking with him, he could not understand what it said. </p>
         <p n="27">27. Three Fathers used to go and visit blessed <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> every year and two of them used to discuss their thoughts and the salva- tion of their souls with him, but the third always remained silent and did not ask him anything. After a long time, Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said to him, 'You often come here to see me, but you never ask me any- thing,' and the other replied, 'It is enough for me to see you, Father.'</p>
          <p n="28">28. They said that a certain old man asked God to let him see the Fathers and he saw them all except Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>. So he asked his guide, 'Where is Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>?' He told him in reply that in the place where God is, there <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> would be.</p>
          <p n="29">29. A brother in a monastery was falsely accused of fornication and he arose and went to Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>. The brethren also came from the monastery to correct him and bring him back. They set about proving that he had done this thing, but he defended himself and denied that he had done anything of the kind. Now Abba Paphnutius, who is called Cephalus, happened to be there, and he told them this parable: 'I have seen a man on the bank of the river buried up to his knees in mud and some men came to give him a hand to help him out, but they pushed him further in up to his neck.' Then Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said this about Abba Paphnutius: 'Here is a real man, who can care for souls and save them.' All those present were pierced to the heart by the words of the old man and they asked forgiveness of the brother. So, admonished by the Fathers, they took the brother back to the monastery.</p>
         <p n="30">30. Some say of Saint <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> that he was 'Spirit-borne', that is, carried along by the Holy Spirit, but he would never speak of this to men. Such men see what is happening in the world, as well as knowing what is going to happen.
31. One day Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> received a letter from the Emperor Constantius, asking him to come to Constantinople and he won- dered whether he ought to go. So he said to Abba Paul, his disciple, 'Ought I to go?' He replied, 'If you go, you will be called <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName>; but if you stay here, you will be called Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName>.'</p>
         <p n="32">32. Abba <persName ref="#m1">Anthony</persName> said, 'I no longer fear God, but I love Him. For love casts out fear.' (John 4.18)</p>
       <p n="33">33. He also said, 'Always have the fear of God before your eyes. Remember him who gives death and life. Hate the world and all that is in it. Hate all peace that comes from the flesh. Renounce this life, so that you may be alive to God. Remember what you have prom- ised God, for it will be required of you on the day of judgement. Suffer hunger, thirst, nakedness, be watchful and sorrowful; weep, and groan in your heart; test yourselves, to see if you are worthy of God; despise the flesh, so that you may preserve your souls.'</p>
       <p n="34">34. Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> once went to visit Abba Amoun in Mount Nitria and when they met, Abba Amoun said, 'By your prayers, the number of the brethren increases, and some of them want to build more cells where they may live in peace. How far away from here do you think we should build the cells?' Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'Let us eat at the ninth hour and then let us go out for a walk in the desert and explore the country.' So they went out into the desert and they walked until sunset and then Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'Let us pray and plant the cross here, so that those who wish to do so may build here. Then when those who remain there want to visit those who have come here, they can take a little food at the ninth hour and then come. If they do this, they will be able to keep in touch with each other without distraction of mind.' The distance is twelve miles.</p>
   <p n="35">35. Abba <persName ref="#m1" >Anthony</persName> said, 'Whoever hammers a lump of iron, first decides what he is going to make of it, a scythe, a sword, or an axe. Even so we ought to make up our minds what kind of virtue we want to forge or we labour in vain.'</p>
  <p n="36">36. He also said, 'Obedience with abstinence gives men power over wild beasts.'</p>
 <p n="37">37. He also said, 'Nine monks fell away after many labours and were obsessed with spiritual pride, for they put their trust in their
own works and being deceived they did not give due heed to the commandment that says, "Ask your father and he will tell you." ' (Deut. 32.7)</p>
  <p n="38">38. And he said this, 'If he is able to, a monk ought to tell his elders confidently how many steps he takes and how many drops of water he drinks in his cell, in case he is in error about it.'</p>
             
            </div>
<div type="section" n="beta">
      <p n="1">  1. Abba <persName xml:id="m4"> Doulas</persName>, the disciple of Abba Bessarion said, 'One day when we were walking beside the sea I was thirsty and I said to Abba Bessarion, "Father, I am very thirsty." He said a prayer and said to me, "Drink some of the sea water." The water proved sweet when I drank some. I even poured some into a leather bottle for fear of being thirsty later on. Seeing this, the old man asked me why I was taking some. I said to him, "Forgive me, it is for fear of being thirsty later on." Then the old man said, "God is here, God is everywhere."'</p>
      <p n="2">   2. Another time when Abba Bessarion had occasion to do so, he said a prayer and crossed the river Chrysoroas on foot and then continued his way. Filled with wonder, I asked his pardon and said, 'How did your feet feel when you were walking on the water?' He replied, 'I felt the water just to my heels, but the rest was dry.'</p>
      <p n="3">     3. On another day, while we were going to see an old man, the sun was setting. So Abba Bessarion said this prayer, 'I pray you, Lord, that the sun may stand still till we reach your servant,' and that is what happened.</p>
      <p n="4">    4. On another day, when I came to his cell I found him standing at prayer with his hands raised towards heaven. For fourteen days he remained thus. Then he called me and told me to follow him. We went into the desert. Being thirsty, I said to him, 'Father, I am thirsty.' Then, taking my sheepskin, the old man went about a stone's throw away and when he had prayed, he brought it back, full of water. Then we walked on and came to a cave where, on entering we found a brother seated, engaged in plaiting a rope. He did not raise his eyes to us, nor greet us, since he did not want to enter into conversation with us. So the old man said to me, 'Let us go; no doubt the old man is not sure if he ought to speak with us.' We continued our journey towards Lycopolis, till we reached Abba John's cell. After greeting him, we prayed, then the old man sat down to speak of the vision which he had had. Abba Bessarion said it had been made known to him that the temples would be over- thrown. That is what happened: they were overthrown. On our return, we came again to the cave where we had seen the brother. The old man said to me, 'Let us go in and see him; perhaps God has told him to speak to us.' When we had entered, we found him dead. The old man said to me, 'Come, brother, let us take the body; it is for this reason God has sent us here.' When we took the body to bury it we perceived that it was a woman. Filled with astonishment, the old man said, 'See how the women triumph over Satan, while we still behave badly in the towns.' Having given thanks to God, who protects those who love him, we went away.</p>
      <p n="5">  5. One day a man possessed with a devil came to Scetis, and they prayed over him, but the devil did not leave him, for it was obstinate. The priests said, 'What can we do against this devil? No one can drive him away, except Abba Bessarion, but if we call him, he will not come, even to the church. Therefore let us do this: since he comes to church early, before anyone else, let us make the possessed sleep here and when he comes, let us keep to our prayer, and say to him, "Abba, awaken the brother." ' This is what they did. When the old man came early, they kept to their prayer and said to him, 'Awaken the brother.' The old man said to him, 'Arise and go.' Immediately the devil departed from him and from that hour he was healed.</p>
      <p n="6">    6. Abba Bessarion said, 'For fourteen days and nights, I have stood upright in the midst of thorn-bushes, without sleeping.'</p>
      <p n="7">   7. A brother who had sinned was turned out of the church by the priest; Abba Bessarion got up and went with him, saying, 'I, too, am a sinner.'</p>
      <p n="8">   8. The same Abba Bessarion said, 'For fourteen years I have never lain down, but have always slept sitting or standing.'</p>
      <p n="9">      9. The same abba said, 'When you are at peace, without having to struggle, humiliate yourself for fear of being led astray by joy which is inappropriate; we magnify ourselves and we are delivered to warfare. For often, because of our weakness, God does not allow us to be tempted, for fear we should be overcome.'</p>
      <p n="10">  10. A brother who shared a lodging with other brothers asked Abba Bessarion, 'What should I do?' The old man replied, 'Keep silence and do not compare yourself with others.'</p>
      <p n="11">   11. Abba Bessarion, at the point of death, said, 'The monk ought to be as the Cherubim and the Seraphim: all eye.'</p>
      <p n="12">   12. Abba Bessarion's disciples related that his life had been like that of a bird of the air, or a fish, or an animal living on earth, passing all the time of his life without trouble or disquiet. The care of a dwelling did not trouble him, and the desire for a particular place never seemed to dominate his soul, no more than the abundance of delights, or the possession of houses or the reading of books. But he seemed entirely free from all the passions of the body, sustaining himself on the hope of good things to come, firm in the strength of his faith; he lived in patience, like a prisoner who is led everywhere, always suffering cold and nakedness, scorched by the sun. He al- ways lived in the open air, afflicting himself on the edge of the desert like a vagabond. Often he found it good to be carried over the sea to distant and uninhabited regions. When he happened to come into pleasanter places where the brethren lived a life in com- mon, he would sit outside at the gate, weeping and lamenting like one shipwrecked and flung back on to the earth. Then if one of the brethren coming out found him there, sitting like one of the poor beggars living in the world, and filled with compassion approached him, asking, 'Man, why are you weeping? If you are in need of something, as far as we can we will see you receive it, only come in, share our table and rest yourself.' He would reply, 'I cannot live under a roof so long as I have not found again the riches of my house,' adding that he had lost great riches in various ways. 'I have fallen amongst pirates, I have suffered shipwreck, I have dis- honoured my rank, becoming unknown, famous as I was.' The brother, moved by these words, returned, bringing a morsel of bread and giving it him, saying, 'Take this, Father; all the rest, as you say, God will restore to you; home, honour, and riches of which you speak.' But he, bewailing himself yet more, sighed deeply, adding, 'I cannot say if I shall find again those lost good things I seek, but I am still more afflicted, every day suffering the danger of death, having no respite because of my great calamities. For always I must wander, in order to finish my course.'    </p>
  </div>         
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
